<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reviv'd fugitive: A gallant historical novel. Dedicated to Her Highness, the Dutchess of Brunswig, Lunebourg, and Zell.</title>
            <author>Belon, P. (Peter)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1204B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12725019</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12725019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66334</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66334)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1030:21 or 2132:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reviv'd fugitive: A gallant historical novel. Dedicated to Her Highness, the Dutchess of Brunswig, Lunebourg, and Zell.</title>
                  <author>Belon, P. (Peter)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bentley, in Russel-Street, in Covent-Garden.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: P.B.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 1030:21 identified as Wing B1858 (number cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66334:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Reviv'd Fugitive: A Gallant Hiſtorical NOVEL. Dedicated to Her HIGHNESS The DUTCHESS of <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwig, Lunebourg,</hi> and <hi>Zell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-Street,</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66334:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66334:2"/>
            <head>TO HER Serene Highneſs, THE Dutcheſs of <hi>Brunſwig, Lunebourg,</hi> and <hi>Zell.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DIvers PROTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANTS ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſought after Victory through Flight, their Retreat cannot fail of ſuch Adventures as are
<pb facs="tcp:66334:3"/>ſurprizing, and that have very much of the Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Air. Thoſe poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have been aſſaulted in ſo many manners, that they are become ingenious in Intreagues, and in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out unknown Ways, to deceive the ſubtlety and vigilance of their Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, which might have forc'd them to ſerve that which is not God, in its own Nature. This <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd Fugitive</hi>'s a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion
<pb facs="tcp:66334:3"/>to a ſtrange Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was very great, thoſe attempts which ſhe has made to prevent her ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any ſhare in it, have been as great. She has overcome her ſelf to maſter thoſe Obſtacles, which were oppos'd to her Liberty, and that Providence which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally gives its bleſſing to thoſe Cares which we take not to be ſeparated from the true Religion, has govern'd all the ſteps which ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:66334:4"/>has made to avoid ſo ſad a ſeparation, and has ſnatch'd her more than once out of the jaws of Death, that ſhe might at laſt ſecure a Good, which by the Goſpel is termed the Good Part, and the ſole neceſſary thing. I addreſs to you, <hi>Madam,</hi> the Relation of it; with all the reſpect due to your Merits and Elevation. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Reaſons ought to make me fear that I may
<pb facs="tcp:66334:4"/>be blam'd for taking the liberty to offer you ſo ſmall a thing, and I ought to have fear'd to expoſe my ſelf in ſo great a Light. But I take Heart, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and I deſpair not, but that you will look on this ſmall Piece with a favourable Eye, and that you will have ſo much boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as to deſcend to this <hi>Reviv'd Fugitive,</hi> all neglected as ſhe is. I have cauſe to believe ſo,
<pb facs="tcp:66334:5"/>when I repreſent to my ſelf how great the Love is, and how ſtrong the application, which you have for our Religion; what will not be your joy to ſee her Triumph in her Perſon over thoſe terrible Temptations, which Love, and Intereſt, and the Examples and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations of a Brother have aſſail'd her with: That in her Adventures there has been ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Circumſtances,
<pb facs="tcp:66334:5"/>that are not wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of your Highneſſes Curioſity, and that being of a Province, which the Heavens has honour'd with ſo Illuſtrious a Birth, as that of your Highneſs; ſhe does hope that you will not diſapprove her Ambition, to treat you with a Diſh of your own Countrey fare; ſhe even flatters her ſelf with the thoughts that you will concern your ſelf in your Country Womans evil
<pb facs="tcp:66334:6"/>and good fortunes, and that you will be pleas'd to unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry your ſelf ſome moments, in the conſideration of thoſe dreadful dangers, with which her Life has been threatned, and of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful manner by which ſhe has been free'd from them. May the Heavens, Madam, cover yours with its powerful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and continue plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully to ſhowre on your Highneſs its Bleſſings,
<pb facs="tcp:66334:6"/>and on your Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. Theſe are the Vows which are made with all the Zeal imaginable, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>MADAM,</hi> Your moſt Serene Highneſſes Moſt Humble, and Moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>P. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66334:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66334:7"/>
            <head>THE Reviv'd Fugitive: A NOVEL.</head>
            <p>LOve never did kindle ſo bright a flame, as that which <hi>Madmoiſelle</hi> of <hi>Charlieu</hi> did preſerve in her heart for the Knight St. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> notwithſtanding all the Reaſons which ſhe thought to have to drive it from thence, ſtrengthned with that great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedneſs which ſhe has always profeſs'd. And peradventure, that there was never ſeen ſuch a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66334:8"/>as that of the Knight St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> for the Charming <hi>Madmoiſelle</hi> of <hi>Charlieu.</hi> They were both of one Province, but the Knight's inclinations having led him to make his firſt Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigns in a very young Age, he had not had time to obſerve the Beauty of a Perſon who was then but in her Spring, and in a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Delineation. Wherefore, it was not till ſhe was at <hi>Paris,</hi> at the Opera of <hi>Phaeton,</hi> that he learnt that which he had remain'd ignorant of till then. He was come to Court to ſolicite for a a vacant Employ at Court, and the Lady's Brother, to follow a Sute in the grand Chamber. That rencounter of Buſineſs was to ſignifie ſomething to him, and did prognoſticate to his indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency ſome conſiderable Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that made him to lend to the Ornaments of the Theatre
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66334:8"/>but an indifferent attention; and while agreeable Muſick did poſſeſs his Ear, he had no Eyes, but for a young Stranger, who was eaſie to be diſtinguiſh'd from the reſt, by her own Perſon.</p>
            <p>He had ſome knowledge of all the Beauties that made a figure at <hi>Paris,</hi> and the Charmes of that new Object oblig'd him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach himſelf of neglect, not without ſevere reflections: He enquir'd of a Gentleman of his acquaintance, Whether that Face was new to him; and becauſe he could no be well inform'd by him, he flatter'd himſelf with the hopes to learn more of her at the going out of the Palace.</p>
            <p>Fortune did favour him in that, for having had her always in view, it luckily happen'd, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify his Curioſity, that a Prieſt who carried the Sacrament to a ſick Perſon, paſſing by at that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66334:9"/>time, ſhe haſtily turn'd back in the Alley, to get to her Coach before the great Gate, where ſhe order'd it ſhould wait for her.</p>
            <p>Thoſe marks of a true right Hugonor, or Proteſtant, were not capable to divert him from the ſatisfaction he propos'd to inform himſelf throughly at <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranton,</hi> which is the place where thoſe of the Reformed Religion have a Church allow'd them. He returned to his Inn, well ſatisfied with ſo happy a diſcovery, and reſolv'd to go thither the very next Day to Church. But it was his ill fortune not to find there what he ſought after. The King had not yet caus'd the Edict to be Proclam'd, which forbids the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots to ſuffer any Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in their Aſſemblies; and that which might have rais'd ſome ſcruple in the Knight, (who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66334:9"/>was an abſolute worthy Perſon) could not yet produce any in him. He remain'd in the Church very quiet during the whole Sermon, which that Day was deliver'd by an eminent Preacher; and he being not a Romaniſt by meer ſtubbornneſs and Caprichio, he found nothing in it that was either horrid or black.</p>
            <p>This firſt queſt having ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo ill, he thought to have miſtaken himſelf in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and he began to attribute to hazard and meer chance that fear which his pretended Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary had been put in the Day before. He return'd to <hi>Paris</hi> in a greater diſorder than ever, and almoſt dead with deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieving ſo delicate a Beauty. He run over all the choiſeſt parts of the City in hopes to find her; he often walk'd in the Tuilleries, and in that odd kind of uneaſineſs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66334:10"/>he would know, at what rate ſo ever, the Name and Birth of ſo rare an Object. One Day that the Weather was very fair, and that he was ſeriouſly thinking in the moſt remote part of the Labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth on the oddneſs of his Stars, he heard his own Name mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned very near to him. <q>I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, <hi>ſaid a Lady to a friend of hers,</hi> that Monſieur of St. <hi>Hubert</hi> is brave, that he has a great deal of ſence and diſcernment, with all that can be requir'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides to nicely carry on an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treague; there is ſomething in his Air which Charmes at firſt ſight; and I no ſooner had ſeen him, but I diſtinguiſhed him from the Croud; but my dear Child, he is a Man, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs that he is as apt as others to run into thoſe defects ſo incident to Men of ſence; I mean Levity and Indiſcretion.</q>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66334:10"/>This Diſcourſe being expreſſed after a very tender Manner, had render'd him extreamly attentive, and peradventure he might have drawn ſome light from thence, if the coming of two other La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies into that Walk, where he ſtood before unſeen, had not diſturb'd the others Converſation who ſought out a more retir'd place, leaving that Poſt ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to our Knight.</p>
            <p>He, not to loſe any time, did all he could to rejoyn them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and having ſlided along the Walks, he at laſt got to the appointed place, but all did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear, and with much to do he gather'd up a <hi>Billet</hi> half cover'd over with Leaves; he knew not whether he had beſt to read it immediately, and his great deſire to follow the Ladies had hindred him from it, if by chance he had not ſeen in it the word Love
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66334:11"/>writ in a large Character. This Onſet is too fair not to peruſe the reſt, ſaid he preſently to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; then having laid it quite open, he found in it what follows.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>BILLET.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LOve affords me leſs quiet than ever, Madam, and I heartily wiſh that in granting me the one, you were pleaſed to afford me the other alſo. I thought that Lovers were not made to ſuffer Eternally, or at leaſt, that ſomething was to be born of them, yet I find quite the contrary in adoring you; you are ſtill the ſame, as well as your Charms; and if after you have let me know I was not wholly indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to you, you ſtill treat me as an Enemy, I ſhall doubtleſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There needed not ſo much to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66334:11"/>render our Knight a Philoſopher, and to lead him into ſerious. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections; but he believ'd it a point of Prudence, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to his quiet, firſt to know thoſe Ladies who had nam'd him, and who probably had loſt the <hi>Billet.</hi> He run to the moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented Avenue, and his ſurprize was ſomewhat great, to ſee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thence that Perſon whom he ſought in all places, accompanied with another Lady; he preſently imagin'd that it was they who had nam'd him, and burning with a vehement deſire to ſpeak to them, he was draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near with that Deſign, when they put on their Masks, and got into a Neighbouring Walk. He therefore was contented with ſimply obſerving them; and being joyn'd by a Friend, he thought he might without any more ado go and reſt himſelf on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66334:12"/>a Bench, with him, of which the Ladies had already made Choice. There were others alſo ſitting there, and every body being very particular, his Curioſity inſpired him to go and give a Servant Orders who waited for him at the Garden Gate, to be in readineſs to follow that Coach which he ſhould ſhew him, and to give him a faithful account of it.</p>
               <p>He was ſcarce got out, when a little Foot-boy, having enquired of his Chair-men, whether that was Monſieur of St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> did haſtily deliver him a Letter, of which it had been ſaid, <hi>That He himſelf ſhould bring back the Anſwer.</hi> He preſently imagin'd it to be one of thoſe obſcene <hi>Billets</hi> with which Debauch'd Women are wont to Regale Perſons by little expreſs Meſſages; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving caſt it on the Ground, he was making an end to order his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66334:12"/>Man what he had to do, when the unknown Lady came, got into her Coach, and ſteer'd her Courſe towards the <hi>Red-Bridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Knight having made a ſign to his Man, he ran as faſt as he could after it, ſo that the hopes to learn before Night, where dwelt that Beautiful Perſon; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given him time to reflect on what he had lately done, he ſought again after his <hi>Billet,</hi> vex'd that he had not read it; and by good fortune having found it again in the ſame place where he had thrown it, he paſs'd his time in the peruſal of it, expecting his Spies return.</p>
               <p>Judging by what it contain'd, that it was an Anſwer to that which he had found in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth, he was in ſo great an amazement that he had much to do to get out of it. He was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that the Lady lov'd paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66334:13"/>the Gentleman for whom it was deſign'd, and at the ſame time fancying that it was his fair unknown Creature, who appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently was pierc'd with a violent Love for ſome other, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd thereat an unexpreſſible trouble; The Miſtake was too evident to draw any Conſequences from thence to his advantage; he did not know her, he had never ſpoken to her, far from having any Intreague with her, and the Errour was but too viſible to be miſtaken in it.</p>
               <p>Mean time he was bemoaning his Deſtiny, and in his Complaint he thought on his Adventure with ſo much application, that three Officers came up to him which he did not perceive. You pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a little too much in Publick, our dear Kinſman, <hi>ſaid one of the three to him,</hi> who was effectually of the ſame Family; and if you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66334:13"/>were in humour to come to —to diſſipate, at the favour of a little Debauch, that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy which overcomes you, we ſhould all be oblig'd to you for it. 'Laſs! poor Man! <hi>ſaid another,</hi> doubtleſs ſome Angel has appear'd to him in the Garden, which has raviſh'd him into an Extaſie; and, if I miſtake not, <hi>added the third,</hi> he has met there with <hi>Rue</hi> and <hi>Parſlee.</hi> Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Knight, <hi>ſaid they all three to him at once,</hi> he is now in his Noviciate of Love, he is now a right Knight, a Knight in all the forms, and without Circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, farewel to all Pleaſures, and to all the <hi>Philles's.</hi> Theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliments did ſomewhat amaze him, being partly got out of it, he diſguis'd as well as he could the troubles of his Mind. You are too gay by half, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd he, ſmiling, and if you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66334:14"/>had buſineſſes at Law, you would not ſo frequently think of running over all the beſt Treaters of <hi>Paris;</hi> go your ways you idle Fellows, <hi>continu'd he,</hi> one ſmall grain of folly would not do amiſs, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you a little wiſer, and more moderate; you are <hi>Horaces,</hi> and meer Slaves to your paſſions! upon this, they endeavour'd to take him along with them, and all his reſiſtance had been in vain, if he had not thought on a come off which ſucceeded to his mind.</p>
               <p>Theſe troubleſome Men being gone at laſt, he plung'd himſelf more deeply than ever in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the two <hi>Billets;</hi> and having eaſily rectify'd them by comparing, he abſolutely conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that there was ſome recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Love, and that he ſhould do very ill to dive any further in that Miſtery. But who knows not, that it is the weakneſs of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66334:14"/>the Braveſt Souls, to cleave to all that appears the moſt difficult to perform; and the more trouble there is to overcome, the more Glorious ſeems to them the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievement. This Perſon made it a point of Honour to puſh this Adventure to the end, and to give himſelf up to the government of his good or ill Star; he once more read the laſt <hi>Billet,</hi> which was writ in the following terms.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>BILLET.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Had foreſeen that you would make me ſome Reproaches, and I might have prepar'd beforehand this Anſwer for you. I know your ways, and if I miſtake not, you pretend to act Souldier-like every where; but learn, that there is a vaſt difference betwixt to Love, and to Fight, and that a Lover can never Triumph, but in his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66334:15"/>Defeat. This is a Leſſon of which you may profit, if it is not your own fault. Farewell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ha! moſt charming unknown Perſon, cry'd he to himſelf at this concluſion, what Diſpoſitions ſhould I find in my ſelf to obey you? and with what joy ſhould I become your Scholar? But you already love, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not complain that love has im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed ſuch extraordinary charms. While he was thus Philoſophiſing on that Conſtellation, his Man, quite out of breath, came to give him an account at large of his Commiſſion? He told him, that he knew poſitively where that Perſon dwelt whom he had fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, That it was a Royal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, abounding in Servants, and that he would conduct him to't when he pleas'd.</p>
               <p>This Relation ended, he would
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66334:15"/>not defer going thither; his Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man follow'd his Servant, and great was his ſurprize to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf carry'd to the Palace of <hi>Mars,</hi> whoſe Attendants 'tis likely his Man had taken for Livery-men: He was ready to correct him for his groſs miſtake; and if the ſmall ſtay which he had made in <hi>Paris,</hi> having been but one week in that City, had not excuſed him, he had at that very moment made tryal of the effect of his ill humour; yet he reſolved to ſee there that Perſon which caus'd him ſo much trouble.</p>
               <p>Nor had he fail'd ſo to do, if that the ſame Curioſity which had drawn her to behold that ſtately Structure, had not invited her to go elſewhere to do the like alſo. He was forced to reſt ſatisfy'd as well as he could; and Monſieur of <hi>Louis</hi> being but juſt alighted there from <hi>Meudon,</hi> to viſit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66334:16"/>to his cuſtom that Houſe, all whoſe Inhabitants conſider him as their Patron; he left off his purſuit, to mention his buſineſs to him, and the opportunity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo favourable, he receiv'd from him ſuch an anſwer as he could wiſh for, with Orders to go to <hi>Verſailles</hi> in few days.</p>
               <p>This beginning of Love having thus given place to his Ambition, he was punctual to obſerve his Directions, and he receiv'd his brief with ſuch eaſe as is rare to be found with ſuch Great Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State: who to ſupport himſelf againſt that envy which is inſeparable from his place, ſeeks but after little other protection, than that which he finds in his Maſters good will and favour. He gain'd by ſo generous a proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, St. <hi>Hubert</hi>'s whole eſteem, who had no other regret to ſee him in ſo great an elevation, but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66334:16"/>becauſe it left him without the power to expreſs his acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments to him for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Of truth he is naturally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging, and that which fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently cauſes Men to paſs from Love, to indifferency, does on the contrary, more ſtrongly kindle in him the heat of his paſſion. Wherefore he has never given that way any cauſe of Complaint, and it may be ſaid, that he perfectly knows the Art of Love without that of ſeigning. That Journey which had acquir'd him a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Employ, had not however quite ſettled his mind, he had thought himſelf unhappy to go for <hi>Nancy,</hi> where his Orders required him to be, without having ſpoken to her whoſe Orders had been yet more precious to him.</p>
               <p>He was returning in his uſual dumps, and was already croſſing the Wood of <hi>Beulogne,</hi> when he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66334:17"/>found himſelf ſtopp'd by two or three confus'd Voices, mixt with ſome breakings forth of Laughter, which ſeem'd to come from the thickeſt part of that Forreſt, and by a Picture-Caſe which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd to ſparkle in the Mudd, he preſently alighted, and having taken it up with ſome haſte, he was extreamly ſurpriz'd at the opening of it, to find the Copy of that Perſon, whoſe Original he ſought after in all places. He reckon'd much on that rencounter, and believing there would be no hurt in drawing near to that place whence the noiſe came, he commanded his people to wait for him.</p>
               <p>He had not made many ſteps, but he perceiv'd the Viſcount St. <hi>Hubert</hi> his Couſin, with ſome Ladies, which for having been overturn'd in the Dirt, thought they had a great cauſe of laughter,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66334:17"/>that their fall had not been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd with any ſiniſter Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, and that they were quit of it, for having given as they fell ſome kiſſes to the Viſcount. Mean time their Coach being broke, it had been ſent back to <hi>Paris,</hi> and they expected another in that part of the Forreſt. He then did ſoon judge that the Picture had been loſt by that accident, and not believing himſelf oblig'd to mention it ſo ſoon, he offer'd to that fair Company his Coach, to go to <hi>Verſailles,</hi> where he alſo reſolv'd to return. The Ladies did long refuſe his offer; and had not the Viſcount labour'd to make them accept of it, he had been entirely refus'd.</p>
               <p>There were four convenient places in it he convinc'd them that he could diſpoſe of his Kinſman, and that it would be ridiculous not to improve his offers; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66334:18"/>they having ſeated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they continued their way. This diverſion had been concluded on two days before with thoſe two Ladies, who had dexterouſly ingag'd St. <hi>Hubert</hi> to accompany them, not but that he had very preſſing buſineſs in Town, where a Miſtreſſes nicity did oblige him to obſerve very exact meaſures. But being naturally very officious, and they very intimate with him, he had impos'd upon himſelf to be of that Match. They were going to give a Viſit to a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, which was to laſt ſome days. Some days, reply'd the Knight to his Kinſman's ear, ſo ſoon as he heard it, ſome days at <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles:</hi> faith, Vicount, I fancy thou wilt have but an ill time of it, and if I am not miſtaken, <hi>Paris</hi> would divert thee much better than <hi>Verſailles.</hi> The Court has ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of buſtle in it, <hi>continu'd he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66334:18"/>aloud, in a foppiſh tone, which fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently makes ſollitude to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to all its Charms; ſo many Circumſtances of cautiouſneſs and exactneſs are uneaſie; and for my part, I never go, but when I think I have ſome buſineſs there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this the Ladies diſcours'd on the pleaſures of the Court, and of the Country, not giving St. <hi>Hubert</hi> any time to anſwer, who was almoſt dead with deſire to have the Knight clear his Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; and thoſe Diſcourſes having put him in mind of a Preſent which he had lately receiv'd, he put his hand to his Pocket, and having not found there what he ſought after, he two or three times chang'd Countenance. It was a Bracelet of his Miſtreſſes hair, which he had obtain'd after divers inſtances, the loſs of which, did grieve him mortally.</p>
               <p>He preſently fancy'd that it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66334:19"/>might have faln out at that place where they had over-turn'd, and not being able to diſguiſe his uneaſineſs, he got out of the Coach ſo ſoon as they were at their Journies end, to ſend People to make an exact ſearch after it. The Knight who had taken notice of that Concern, believ'd that it was on the account of the Picture, and taking delight to leave in ſome trouble a Perſon whom he thought too happy, he took no notice of what he had taken up: he ſaid to himſelf, that he might well keep for ſome time the Copy of ſo Charming an Original, whoſe firſt ſight had ſo violently diſturb'd him. Thoſe diſorders continu'd not long, the preſence of the Ladies did at leaſt impoſe ſome Conſtraint on them; and feigning on all hands very cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, they got to an Inn to reſt themſelves, cackled more than
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66334:19"/>ever, and at laſt conducted the Gentlemen to the young Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſſes Lodgings.</p>
               <p>They were no leſs ſurpriz'd the one than the other in approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that Lady; they Saluted her, and the Viſcount ſeeming not to know her, was reſolv'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſerious, if the two others could have forborn to Laugh. In this intricacy, the Knight thought there was ſome Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and, not knowing what to think of ſuch an unexpected Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, was in the greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement imaginable, to find that Stranger who had caus'd him ſo much trouble in the Perſon of the Marchioneſs. He drew near to a Window to clear the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the more; and diſtruſting his own Eyes, he drew the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture out of his Pocket, where he obſerv'd the ſame Face, though the Painter had flatter'd never ſo little.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:66334:20"/>
               <p>While they were jeſting with the Viſcount on the frolick his Miſtreſs had put upon him, in cauſing him to make her a Viſit in a place, whence ſhe was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd far diſtant, he had time to recollect himſelf from the diſorder that ſurprize had put him in; and contenting himſelf with ſtorming againſt his ill Fortune, he at laſt appear'd leſs diſcountenanc'd than any. Mean time, he return'd a Thouſand Thanks to the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for the advantageous Cheat had been put upon him; and all tranſported with joy, as he was, he loſt himſelf in the the young Marchioneſs's Looks, and in the marks of ſo particular a favour. The Knights preſence did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what reſtrain her fancy on that Article, and though her Lover frequently repeated that he was not to be ſuſpected, ſhe judg'd it convenient not to admit the Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66334:20"/>to the height of Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and turning the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on what had happen'd to them on the Road, ſhe then gave clearly to underſtand that all had been done by her Command, that ſhe might have time to get firſt to <hi>Verſailles,</hi> which gave the Count occaſion to ſay the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanteſt things in the World on innocent malice.</p>
               <p>Yet would the loſs of his Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let come by fits into his Mind, and the Knight, who omitted not to obſerve the leaſt alteration in his Face, did ſecretly applaud himſelf on his happy meeting with the Picture. This joy ſet him in a very gay Humour, and having drawn near to the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Marchioneſs, he ſaid ſo many ingenious and gallant things to her, that the two others were diſturb'd at it. He ſpoke to them in their turn alſo, and for the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66334:21"/>firſt Acquaintance, he had made a very fair Progreſs.</p>
               <p>This was about the time that a Ballet was to be Danc'd at Court; the Court was to be very Magnificent, and thoſe Rejoicings which were but the Preludes to the Carouſel, of which ſo much has been ſaid, having laſted ſome Days to divert ſome ſtrange Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, it retain'd our Troop there a whole Week alſo, after which they return'd to <hi>Paris.</hi> Mean time, the Viſcount had had no News of his Bracelet, and the Knight had always in his Mind the advantage which he had over his Love. Yet at laſt his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity prevailing over his Intereſt, he reſolv'd to Sacrifice himſelf to his Cozens quiet: He ſtruggled long before he overcame, and taking a firm Reſolution to go and clear that Point with him, he would not defer it one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66334:21"/>longer, for fear of relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into his former weakneſs. He gave him an account in few words of all his whole Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thoſe of the Billets and of the Picture; which he preſented to him. He aſſur'd him, that having been ſo happy as to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from Monſieur <hi>de Louvois,</hi> what he deſir'd, he had no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoughts but to return pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, to that place where his Order ingag'd him to repair, and that he deſired nothing from him but to render himſelf Depoſitary of a Complement for his Miſtreſs, in the fear that a ſecond ſight might inſpire him with new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. The Viſcount raviſh'd with this Generoſity, without Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, did haſtily embrace him, and obſerving by his Eyes that he ſpoke in good earneſt, they both ſo molified their Boſoms, that they had much to do to avoid
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66334:22"/>ſhedding of Tears. They gave to each other a Thouſand aſſurances of Friendſhip; and if the Viſcount had ſo far been Maſter of his Miſtreſs's Heart, as to diſpoſe of it in favour of another, he had endeavour'd to have yielded it to him. He afterwards took the Two Billets, the one of his, the other of his Miſtreſs's Hand, the Porter having doubtleſs miſtaken, through the conformity of Names, and the Rencounter, ſeeing the other had paſs'd but a moment before by the ſame place, when he had preſs'd him to be of their little Debauch: As to the Picture, he confeſs'd 'twas none of his, but it extreamly reſembling his Miſtreſs, he ſo preſt the Knight to go a long with him to clear the buſineſs with her, that at laſt he reſolved to do it.</p>
               <p>They found her in a very neat Dreſs, though negligent; and it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66334:22"/>was eaſie to be obſerv'd, that if dreſſing became her, ſhe alſo did very much ſet off her Dreſs by her own Luſtre, by her Air, and by her Shape. She look'd on the Picture with amazement, and made anſwer when they would have made it paſs for hers, that it never had been ſo; that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore ſhe knew her ſelf ſo well, that ſhe would never have reſign'd it into the hands of any Perſon capable of ſo great a neglect. Thoſe laſt Words were Reproaches to the Viſcount, who could not forget the loſs he had made; he was ſenſibly mov'd at it; and if his Billet had not given him occaſion to convince her of a careleſſneſs, of which he himſelf was but too guilty, he had not deferr'd his own puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he reſolv'd however not to mention any thing of it to her; and the Knight being fallen into
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66334:23"/>a Converſation, in order to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain ſome things of the Opera, the Labirinth, and the Hoſpital, he then complain'd of the loſs of the Billet, and expreſs'd a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, in which his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was not in the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd. She got out of that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with a look that pierc'd him to the very Soul, and which gave him to underſtand more than any thing elſe, that her tenderneſs had not the leaſt ſhare in that accident. That was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an abſolute Command to be ſilent, nether did the Knight know what to ſay, when ſhe declar'd that the Opera, and the Hoſpital of <hi>Mars,</hi> had no part in her ſtory: That of truth ſhe had been at the Tuilleries that Day he mention'd; and that as to the other circumſtances, of having put on her Mask, and retir'd in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfrequented Walk to reſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66334:23"/>her ſelf, all that was new to her. That was expreſs'd in ſuch an affirmative accent, that he knew not what to imagine. He ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly beheld her without ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and the more he look'd on her, the more he confirm'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Error. Finally, he was quite undeceiv'd by aſſured Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and what paſs'd at firſt in his Mind as a great truth, appear'd to him at laſt but as a meer illuſion. He knew not what to conjecture of that Face, that was ſo reſembling that of this Marchioneſs, he five or ſix times felt his own Pulſe, to know whether he was not in a Feaver; or at leaſt, whether he was not turn'd Viſionariſt: And for fear of turning Wizard at <hi>Paris,</hi> he reſolv'd to go out of it the next Day, with his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, which he began to find a Thouſand times more real
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66334:24"/>than the Perſon which it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</p>
               <p>He inſtantly took his leave of thoſe Two Lovers; and having gone towards Night to his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to bid him farewel, he found him in the reſolution to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him in his Journey. The deſign which had been fram'd on <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> had oblig'd eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Officer to repair to his Poſt againſt the 15th. of <hi>September.</hi> That oblig'd the Viſcount to quit his Miſtreſs, to join his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that was at <hi>Metz;</hi> he put back their Journey for Three Days, to beſtow them wholly on his Miſtreſs; after which, they both took Poſt in the great Road to <hi>Strasburg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Every one is ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of the firſt Bombarding of that Town; Monſieur the Marſhal of <hi>Crequi,</hi> having been oblig'd, becauſe of the cold Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66334:24"/>to put off that Enterpriſe till the next Spring; mean time, poſſeſſing all the Poſts which cut off all Communications, and form'd the Blockado, the Troops retir'd into their Winter Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the Viſcount finding himſelf at liberty to return to his Amours, or rather to conclude his Marriage with the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who had frequently writ to him; he receiv'd one the Night before his ſetting forth, which overcame him with grief. We have already ſaid, that ſhe was very nice, and that quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which ſhe deriv'd more from a ſtrong Paſſion, than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Principle, had made her to draw conſequences which were prejudiciable to her Lover. This is what ſhe expreſs'd of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:66334:25"/>
               <head>BILLET.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Was already convinc'd of the levity of Men in General; but I believ'd at leaſt that it was not without exception, and that I might truſt your fidelity. Mean time you have deceiv'd me, and the only comfort that I have left, is, that I never was but half ſo. My weakneſs did not proceed without Reflections, and I no longer doubt, after your treachery, that diſtruſt is the ſole preſervation of our Sex.</hi> Adieu.</p>
               <p>Thrice did he read over the ſame Words, to find out a ſenſe contrary to the true one; he as oft examin'd himſelf without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending whence ſo ſudden an effect ſhould proceed; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times believing himſelf guilty, then anon again innocent, he fell
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66334:25"/>into a dumps, out of which he had much ado to retrieve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. All this while his Love re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd him nothing, he found nothing in his paſt conduct that Condemn'd him; but according to that Maxime, that will have the Lover to be always in the wrong, he at laſt concluded, that his Miſtreſs had all the right imaginable. He was to go juſtify himſelf without delay. Scarce did he give himſelf time ſufficient to go and embrace his Kinſman, and to declare to him the neceſſity of that precipitation.</p>
               <p>This had wiſh'd to have return'd along with him, and nothing had prevented him, had not a Family concern, which requir'd his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, call'd him home. He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly went thither, and finding himſelf oblig'd to paſs there part of the Winter, he no longer thought of <hi>Paris</hi> but with ſighs.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66334:26"/>He had a certain grief at it, which diſcovering it ſelf ſufficiently on his face, did oblige him to ſeek after a thouſand occaſions to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate it.</p>
               <p>He frequently went to Hunt, to which the moderate Climate of his Province did much contribute: he made matches of Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with his whole Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and thus endeavour'd to recompence himſelf in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, of thoſe pleaſures which he loſt there. A Proteſtant Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, named <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> was one of his firſt acquaintances; he was very agreeable, and the Charms of a Siſter of St. <hi>Hubert</hi> drawing him frequently thither, he found with him wherewith to paſs his time. It is true, that Madmoiſelle of St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> taking delight to hear him, had conſequently the greateſt ſhare in his Viſits; but after all, the Knight had ſome
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66334:26"/>ſhare in them alſo: and having taken ſome of thoſe viſits on his own account, he thought himſelf oblig'd to return them him. He therefore went to viſit <hi>Chanlisu</hi> in his Eſtate, and having declar'd that he deſign'd to remain three days with him, the firſt had no other thoughts but to divert him by all manner of means.</p>
               <p>Chance did furniſh him with one which he could not otherwiſe expect; he learnt that St. <hi>Hubert</hi> did paſſionately love Muſick, and that he might be regal'd by the Ears, as well as by the Eyes. He writ to a friend of his in the next Town, to engage a Select number of Choice Perſons, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in Conſorts, to come to his Houſe, with all thoſe Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they uſually employ'd with their Voice. <hi>Chanlieu</hi> was a friend tr every body, and his friend nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to uſe much Entreaties to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66334:27"/>get their Conſent: He gave notice of it to Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> who had been two days in that Town, and having told her that her Brother deſign'd to give an Opera to Monſieur of St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> ſhe reſolv'd to be of the Match, and to agreeably ſurprize them that way. Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> who took no notice that mention had been made of Monſieur, and not of Madmoiſelle St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> did really believe that it was ſhe that had come to viſit her; and on the preſſing ſolicitations of St. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> ſo was that frien'd nam'd, who was a Gentleman of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, ſhe no longer deferr'd to go joyn them. Notice was ſent to Monſieur <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> that he ſhould have cauſe to be ſatisfied, and that his Coach would be expected. Mean time they employ'd their thoughts about what Perſons they ſhould repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66334:27"/>and having all met at the Rendezvous, they were plac'd at the end of the Hall; where the form of an Alcove ſeem'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent a kind of Theatre; at both ends of which, had been ſuſpended two large Sconces, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with Tapers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> which above all did wiſh his Miſtreſs to partake of this Regalia, had engag'd the Knight to write to her; ſo that having them both at his Houſe, he inſenſibly conducted them to the deſign'd place: after which, the ſign being given, the Candles were inſtantly lighted, all the Inſtruments began a prelude, very agreeably maintain'd, and the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera follow'd with great applauſe. The Actors out-did themſelves in this Occaſion; but all overcame St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> when he perceiv'd there that face, who had ſo deeply wounded him at the Opera of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66334:28"/>
                  <hi>Phaeton.</hi> His ſurprize was great at the firſt ſight of ſo agreeable a Company; but he believ'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in an Enchanted place, when he beheld there that Perſon, who began to paſs for an Enchantreſs in his thoughts. He drew near to his Siſter to inform himſelf more particularly of it, when ſhe left the reſt of her Company to come and embrace her, yet ſome ſmall tincture colour'd her face more than ordinary, at the ſight of the Knight, who taking no further notice for the preſent, ſhew'd his reſpects to her.</p>
               <p>That friendſhip which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd ſo great betwixt thoſe two Perſons, fill'd him immediately with joy and pleaſure; he took his time to approach her, and the Conſort having chang'd into a kind of Ball, he made her a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand excuſes for not having known her ſooner. He told her, after a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66334:28"/>gallant manner, that neither his heart nor his eyes had any thing to reproach him with on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that ſhe diſtinguiſh'd her ſelf too much to be deceiv'd, and that no perſon could behold her face, without perceiving divers admirable things. He after that did invite her to Dance, and it ſo falling out according to order, that he was to give her the preference in all reſpects; he ſtill entertain'd her moſt agreeably, he ingenuouſly turn'd his Diſcourſe on the ſtay ſhe had made at <hi>Paris;</hi> and no longer fearing to be deceiv'd, he felt within him a joy that cannot be expreſs'd. He thought there was ſomething ſo ſingular in his Adventures, that he was wrapt up in admiration of them, as well as the Beauty that had produc'd them; and abandoning himſelf blindly to his fate, an ardent paſſion took poſſeſſion of his mind;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66334:29"/>his eyes did no longer belye his heart, and running over his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, he reproach'd himſelf a thouſand times for having ſet up the Marchioneſs in her place in his mind, and for not having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd all that difference which he was ſenſible of at preſent. The truth is, they were extream like one another, and that a little more of youth, and ſoftneſs of features, made all the difference.</p>
               <p>Mean time abundance of things were in agitation in the boſome of St. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> he had long ſince obſerv'd that Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> was the lovelieſt Perſon in the World, but he had never had any thoughts to love her; he liv'd with her as with a friend, for whom he had a great eſteem and friendſhip, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conſequences, and it was in this Company that he firſt found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great alteration in his heart. It
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66334:29"/>continualy ſet before his eyes that Object with all its Charms, and his mind being flatter'd at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, he took in large draughts of a moſt dangerous Poiſon.</p>
               <p>Though he was not altogether of ſo great a Quality as was Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> yet he had ſufficiency of Birth, Wit, and Means, to aſpire to her Conqueſt; beſides that, being both of one Religion, he believ'd that ſufficient to overcome all Obſtacles. He was naturally very undertaking, ſo that in hopes to eaſily make her paſs from friendſhip to Love, he readily embark'd himſelf, and reſolv'd to take juſt meaſures. On the contrary, the Knight was ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid, and conſequently had had but little reſt ſince his return home; he would frame to himſelf ſtrange Monſters to overcome, and if he had been able, he had dive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted himſelf of a paſſion, which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66334:30"/>was to coſt him his whole quiet.</p>
               <p>Alas! what a difficult thing it is to vanquiſh ones ſelf when one Loves much, and how little ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a greatneſs of Soul againſt the power of a violent paſſion? all his ſtruglings were uſeleſs, and Madmoiſelle of St. <hi>Hubert</hi> having obſerv'd a great Change in his Perſon, ſhe was forc'd to preſs him very hard, to get from him an acknowledgement of his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; No Siſter, ſaid he to her, Love ſhall not long be my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, I'le be gone to morrow, and Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi>'s Charms ſhall not have leiſure to reaſon on their Victory, after their Triumph over me: Ah! thou beautiful <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonot,</hi> how Catholick are thy Charms, and your Perſon little agreeing with what is told us of your Religion? he had proceeded in his Complaints, had not his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter made a full ſtop there, to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66334:30"/>reaſon on his paſſion: She lov'd <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> and ſhe having the ſame difficulties to Combate in her turn, ſhe repreſented to her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he too much magnify'd the Objects, and that thoſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties that appear'd ſo great to him, were not however Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable: that ſhe had formerly much reaſon'd within her ſelf on ſuch a like matter, and that ſhe had found in it more of fear, than of danger.</p>
               <p>Let a Lover ſay what he will, he loves ſtill to be flatter'd, and he cannot be heal'd, without cauſing ſome ſorrow to him. The Knight thought himſelf oblig'd to her for this Diſcourſe, and gave her ſuch acknowledgments of it, as he appear'd not Maſter of; ſhe on her part had great diſpoſitions to ſerve him, her intereſt was viſibly engag'd in it, ſo that ſhe was not to deliberate: ſhe made
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66334:31"/>to her Brother as ingenious a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion as he had done to her, and acknowledging to him her weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Monſieur of <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> who after a long aſſiduouſneſs, had lighted on the key of her heart: They agreed to act joyntly in that buſineſs, for both their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Hubert</hi> did frequently go to <hi>Chanlieu</hi>'s, and the Marqueſs of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> as frequently to the Knight St. <hi>Huberts:</hi> thoſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Viſits did give ſome oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to this laſt to expreſs by his looks what paſs'd in his heart, and his Courtſhip was always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd with ſo Eloquent a languiſhment, that it was not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to obſerve it. He one day told Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> how dear the firſt ſight of her had coſt his Curioſity, with how much earneſtneſs he had ſought after her; his Journey to <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:66334:31"/>his miſtake in another Lady that ſo much reſembled her, and the finding of the Picture. While he was relating theſe things, his Eyes were fix'd upon her, and learning from her delicate mouth ſome particulars which aſſiſted him to unravel thoſe Myſteries, he pull'd the Picture out of his Pocket to compare it with the Original.</p>
               <p>She then told him, <hi>That before ſhe left</hi> Paris <hi>ſhe thought to make uſe of that opportunty to have that Picture drawn, and that having loſt it going to</hi> Verſailles, <hi>he whom ſhe had ſent to ſeek for it where it had been loſt, had there found a Hair-Bracelet garniſh'd with two Lockets, on which ſome Cyphers had been ſet with ſmall Diamonds.</hi> He clear'd further that accident alſo, and ſhe inſiſting to have the Picture return'd to her in reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Bracelet, he was forc'd
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66334:32"/>to call in <hi>Chanlieu</hi> to be judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, who condemn'd his Siſter, &amp; repreſented to her, That ſhe hazarded nothing in leaving in his hands a thing which mear chance had juſtly beſtow'd on him: He alſo advis'd, that the Bracelet ſhould be ſent to the Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that he ſhould have reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution made him of a thing of ſo great value.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> came juſt to be a witneſs to that buſineſs; he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd the Knight's happineſs, and did extend himſelf through the means of the Copy ſo largely on the Original, that ſhe was oblig'd to ſay, <hi>She ſhould take it kindly if they would ſpare her Modeſty.</hi> He was come full of great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, no leſs than to declare his Paſſion to her: St. <hi>Hubert</hi>'s aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduouſneſs had of late given him ſome perplexity; his love did adviſe him to prevent ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66334:32"/>a Rival, wherefore it was with great regret that he was oblig'd to put off his deſign to another time.</p>
               <p>Love leads Perſons into ſtrange Speculations, and frequently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers to amorous Eyes that which would ſtill remain conceal'd to indifferent ones. St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> had never diſcover'd the Knight's love, if he had not burnt in the ſame flame; and though his good hopes had lull'd him aſleep, he having ſtuddy'd the Lovers Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, it of a ſudden fill'd him with apprehenſions, ſo that he would no longer build on the ſmall hopes of a Catholick Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals ſucceſs in ſuch a concern. He knew that Love was of all Religions, and that that I know not what, which is produc'd by a conceal'd Sympathy, was not always to be reſtrain'd by an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy of Belief and of Faith:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66334:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:66334:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:66334:34"/>The perſon concern'd had more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over Qualities capable to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all ſorts of Conſiderations, and he was no leſs to be fear'd by his intricate and ſubtle Wit, than by his Bravery and by his good Meen. There was nothing but his departure for the Army that caus'd him to rejoyce; for at that time the Proteſtant Officers having been diſguſted, St. <hi>Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veur</hi> had quitted his Employ the laſt Campaign, and the Knight was oblig'd to render himſelf at his, within the ſpace of ſix Weeks.</p>
               <p>Wherefore he fore-knowing that ill fate, he manag'd as well as he could all his moments to the beſt advantage for his Love, and loſt none of thoſe in which he could in anywiſe promote his Loves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. He diſcover'd to <hi>Chanlieu</hi> all that he felt for his Siſter. He implor'd his aſſiſtance, and aſſur'd
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66334:34"/>him, That he would be very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of all his good Offices, and they both running the ſame For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, it was no hard thing for him to make him his. They ſwore to one another an eternal Friendſhip, and being parted, the Knight re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to his Siſter, and gave her many thanks. He conjur'd her to believe, that he was ſenſible of her kindneſs to the height he ought to be, and he would give her ſome particular marks of it all his life time; He gave her to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, That it could be but through her means he ſhould be happy, and that Madamoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> loving moſt tenderly her Brother, ſhe might eaſily entertain him in thoſe favourable Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he had for him.</p>
               <p>This proceeding being no new thing to her, he had cauſe to be contented with the Anſwer which ſhe made him, and to give him
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66334:35"/>ſome more eſſential Proofs of it; ſhe feign'd a ſmall Indiſpoſition to obtain a Viſit from that Lady her dear Friend. The Knight adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis'd of this, took care to make her a gallant and magnificent Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and his inclination agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonderfully with his love, it may be concluded, that nothing was omitted; and that he procur'd her all the Divertiſements which the ſeaſon would then afford. He appear'd very earneſt to expreſs to her his Joys, and Madamoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> who had already per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd his Deſigns without her Brother's aſſiſtance, did not appear more reſerv'd than uſually; She politickly believ'd, that that ought not to diminiſh her uſual gaity, and that a Lover ought to underſtand himſelf in his Conjectures. On his part, he had much to do to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his Paſſion from breaking forth with too much violence,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66334:35"/>and he felt a redoubling of the Fitt by ſuch new Charms that he had not perceiv'd before.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> who had ſubtily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd himſelf in that Viſit, was wonderfully griev'd at it; he was of late become the Argus and Spye of all their Actions, and finding but too much cauſe to fear and to allarm himſelf, he loſt the beſt part of his gay Humour; not but that he had a particular Empire over himſelf to diſguiſe what paſs'd in the bottom of his Heart; but let one diſſemble never ſo much, it is ever certain, that Tenderneſs will always manifeſt it ſelf in ſpight of all our greateſt caution, and the moſt ſubtle Perſon, when once grown jealous, cannot long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain himſelf. He was play'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the account of his ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and St. <hi>Hubert</hi> miſtruſting nothing of the truth, did attribute to his Temper that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66334:36"/>from quite another thing. Mean time he perform'd his Duties with great earneſtneſs, and his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter acting mutually with him, Madamoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually meet with ſome Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So many things gave her to apprehend, what ſhe ought to think of the Knight's looks; ſhe had found a great ſtock of Virtue and Honeſty in his Perſon, ſhe knew his Merit; but through all thoſe rare Qualities, her budding Love did affright her, and caus'd her to diſtruſt her ſelf. For tho' amongſt Perſons of Quality, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is no obſtacle to the ſtricteſt Tyes, in theſe latter times ſhe found a great cauſe of apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and though Reaſon ſeem'd to adviſe her to be inflexible in that caſe, ſhe found not ſtrength enough in her ſelf to warrant her love and her weakneſs; mean time ſhe thought that it were prudence
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66334:36"/>in her to avoid the danger: She haſtned her return one day the ſooner, and took her leave of her Friend, accompany'd with Tears.</p>
               <p>But all thoſe Flights were uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; Love follow'd her ſteps, and her Sentiments for the Knight were by half too favourable to her mind: There aroſe a Conflict in her Heart, of which the Succeſs was very uncertain, and Victory waving a long time, nothing was abſolutely decided; She would willingly have cur'd her ſelf to the hazard of her own Quiet, and to that purpoſe having caſt her Eyes on St. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> ſhe an hundred times reſolved to receive him kindly, and as often the Knight's Idea would appear and interpoſe in her Deſigns.</p>
               <p>In the midſt of theſe her Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, ſhe had but little reſt; and not knowing which party to take, ſhe reſign'd the care of her
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66334:37"/>Heart to its own deſtiny. St. <hi>Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veur</hi> who had no time to loſe, having been to ſee her at her own Houſe ſome days after her return, had fitted himſelf with a Billet, to get ſome foreknowledge of his Fate, and <hi>Chanlieu</hi> having taken upon him to dextrouſly convey one from St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> he had given him theſe following Verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Love is not ſuch a Tyrant as ſome ſay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When they think he deſtroys, he does but play;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By the late good 'has done me, I do find</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He's rather to be courted than deelin'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If e're from him I receiv'd any Harms,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Twas in the abſence of</hi> Selinda<hi>'s Charms,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:66334:37"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>After he had with her Picture ſo fir'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My panting Heart, that nothing I deſir'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But to behold th' Original. In vain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of my fruitleſs Inqueſt I did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Without ſucceſs I ſought her far and near,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The more I ſought, the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd my fear</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of loſing hopes and labour; till at laſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One moment recompens'd my Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments paſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No ſooner did I once again be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That charming Creature, but my Hope grew bold;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I quite forgot all the troubles and ſmart</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her ſight and abſence had caus'd in my Heart.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:66334:38"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Pleaſures I receiv'd at this review,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſome few moments did my Life renew.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If Love alone oppos'd my Heart's Deſires,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And was the only thing did damp my Fires,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All the Care, Pains and Sighs, that he could cauſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I ſhould not value to gain her Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our differing in Worſhip 'tis does prove</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>More fatal to my Vows than gentle Love;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But now Religion to my Love muſt yield,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It ſhall ride Conqueror and win the Field.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To my Confeſſors I now bid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieu.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'll conſtantly adore divine</hi> C—</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:66334:38"/>
               <p>Madamoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi>'s Name did ſo juſtly fall in the end of the laſt Verſe, and St. <hi>Hubert</hi>'s Paſſion was ſo lively ſet forth in the whole piece, that it had been left thus imperfect for fear of vexing her; for it had not been difficult to know her ſelf in it at firſt ſight, beſides, his Eyes and Actions had already been very powerful Interpreters: But an odd Accident ſuſpended the reading of them for that time. St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> whom love had conducted thither early that morning, and had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd that when <hi>Chanlieu</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd them to his Siſter, he had told her, they proceeded from the Pen of one of his moſt intimate Friends, thought that he might improve the opportunity: He ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd where ſhe laid them, to peruſe them when alone; He put in their place a Declaration of Love thus worded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:66334:39"/>
               <head>BILLET by way of Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Had formerly the honour to be in the number of your Friends, Madam, and I ſhould always have remain'd in that Calmneſs I enjoy'd, had not Love at laſt made me know the difference there is betwixt it and Friendſhip. I tremble yet at this Confeſſion, and I find my ſelf but too much diſpos'd to behold you after a manner which cannot well be expreſs'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Madamoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> having had a conveniency while they were taking a turn round the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to ſatisfie her Curioſity, ſhe was ſurpris'd to find that Billet in the place of that which ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; Her mind being piercing and ſolid, She had thought that her Brother's intereſt had carry'd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66334:39"/>him to favour the Knight, and that without any further exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that which he had given her came from him: Having found the contrary at the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Billet, ſhe fell into a muſing, out of which ſhe had much to do to get; the hand of him who had writ it was hnown to her, and her Heart perhaps not agreeing with the Contents of it, ſhe was vex'd with her Brother for having taken upon him a buſineſs which extremely diſpleas'd her, and ſhe diſpos'd her ſelf to ill treat them both.</p>
               <p>This vexing gave her a ſecret cauſe to doubt of the fortitude of her Heart, and perſuaded her that it was no longer in a ſtate of making choice; ſhe preſently bent her anger on St. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> and that proceeding which perhaps ſhe had eaſily forgiven in St. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:66334:40"/>did vex her mortally; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did ſhe fail of reproaching to her ſelf that diſtinction which ſhe made, and in repreſenting to her ſelf an hiddeous Picture of Love, wherewith to fortifie her ſelf againſt that which inſenſibly attack'd her, ſhe reſolv'd to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally hate all that was Man, and to inceſſantly oppoſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgency of her own Temper.</p>
               <p>Mean time St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> deſirous to learn originally the effects of his Billet, return'd into her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, and was going to caſt himſelf at her Feet, when a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain look ſeem'd to pronounce the Sentence of his Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>He being naturally of an high Spirit, he thought it would too much offend his Honour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend ſo low; ſo that turning the buſineſs into a meer Gallantry, <hi>Really Madamoiſelle,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I did
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:66334:40"/>not think to offend you in taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of thoſe Bounties you have always expreſs'd to me; it is but for want of underſtanding well what it is to love, that I have made a theft of which I had not well weigh'd the conſequences; but Madamoiſelle, I am ready to expiate my fault in all that you ſhall pleaſe to order me to do: And if I have been too fooliſh, it ſhall make me wiſer for the future: Here are the Verſes which I did ill to take,</hi> added he, preſenting them to her; <hi>and ſeeing I have had the ill fortune to diſpleaſe you in robbing you of them; I foreſee that I do you a ſingular kindneſs in reſtoring them to you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She thought at firſt that St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> gave her the change; ſhe had heard his Diſcourſe with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: She remain'd a moment ſtartled at it, but at laſt having reſolved to remain ſerious, <hi>You
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:66334:41"/>are very inquiſitive and very bold,</hi> ſhe reply'd, <hi>to take upon you the knowledge of my Sentiments, after having ſo ſenſibly offended me; in truth, I know not after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you pretend to juſtifie your ſelf; I know that Friendſhip has its juſt bounds, and that you have this day appear'd to me very different from your ſelf.</hi> This Diſcourſe deliver'd with a little Heat, caus'd him to bluſh and grow pale again, and his Heart panting with Love and Vexation, knew not what party to take; when <hi>Chanlieu</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by his preſence a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation which began to grow warm; he preſently obſerv'd ſome anger on his Siſters face, and gueſſing the cauſe to be the reading of the Verſes which he had given her; he thought he was frown'd upon on that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; he appear'd vex'd at it, and drawing from her coldneſs an
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66334:41"/>ill Omen for his Friend; he let himſelf go to a Sorrow capable to confirm him in his Error. He made a ſign to St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> to follow him out, to diſcourſe with him in the cauſe that could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſo great a Melancholly in ſo ſhort a time; and this laſt finding himſelf confounded with all his Queſtions, cunningly feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a neceſſity of retiring, and took leave of him ſomewhat ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily. He inſtantly run to his Siſter to learn from her ſelf the cauſe of this myſterious departure, finding her more chearful than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhe laid all the cauſe on the unevenneſs of her temper: Yet durſt he not enquire concerning her Sentiments on St. <hi>Hubert</hi>'s Gallantry; He thought it more proper to ſend and Expreſs for him, that he might come and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf of his good or bad Fortune; he fail'd not to be there
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:66334:42"/>the very next day before his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs was up, reſolv'd to declare his Paſſion to her in moſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving terms.</p>
               <p>He felt on this occaſion a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which join'd to his natural timidity, put him into a great conſternation; he alter'd five or ſix times his mind, and at laſt having a little ſetled himſelf, and drawn new vigour from the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Love, he broke that Silence which he had for ſome time kept, he performed it in a manner accompany'd with an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion which did highly grace the beauty of his Complement. He proteſted to her, <hi>That ſhe was not to be offended but at her own Charms for it, that he had reſiſted his Paſſion with vehemency, but that at laſt he had been forc'd to yield to ſo many Charms. You may have ſeen perhaps a ſlight Draught of my Flame, in my Verſes which your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:66334:42"/>gave you yeſterday,</hi> added he, beholding her with a languiſhing Tranſport; <hi>you ought to look for my excuſe but in your Eyes, they are only guilty of the attempt, and all reaſoning is to be laid aſide when one goes about ſo fair a Conqueſt; there is no Learning nor Morals can hold, and the greateſt difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are with eaſe overcome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This fair one having heard him, without ſpeaking, kept ſilence a little while longer, and by that ſhew'd that there paſs'd a great Combat in her mind: She at laſt gave a great ſigh, which ſmother'd part of what ſhe would have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, and ſhe reſted ſatisfy'd in ſaying, <hi>That his Complement was ſo extraordinary, that ſhe knew not what to judge of it, and that the Age was ſufficiently Gallant to have inſpir'd him with Follies, ſo common with the Ingenious; yet I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> continu'd ſhe, <hi>to render you
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:66334:43"/>ſome Juſtice in this Rencounter, and to believe that there is ſome Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in your proceeding, what good would it do you to love me? And if the thing be true, will you not do better to cure your ſelf in time, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to perſiſt to ſee me? Our Religions are at preſent at open Difference, we are cruſh'd down with new Declarations, and it wants but little that the Clergy thinks not of forbidding the Catholicks on pain of Fire not to have any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Intreagues: Believe me, Knight, cure your ſelf, if it be poſſible, and without having occaſion of letting you know what my Sentiments are; be ſatisfy'd that another ſhould not come off ſo eaſily. Ah! Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle,</hi> cry'd he at this long Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <hi>Love is of all Religions, and it becomes not Men to make Laws for him that rules all the World; he little regards dangers, and drawing from himſelf the moſt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:66334:43"/>proper means to his end, he is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ingenuous to bring about what ever he undertakes: No, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle, your Orders are too difficult to perform; and I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways heard ſay, that nothing but Death can free one from ſo fair and ſo ſtrong a Chain as mine is.</hi> He expreſs'd thoſe laſt words with an ingenuity that was capable to mollify her; ſhe ſtood in want of all her Fortitude to prevent him from taking notice of ſome marks; ſo that retiring deeper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Character of ſeverity, ſhe oblig'd him to leave off a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which ſeem'd not to pleaſe her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> who was hearkning, raviſh'd with ſo paſſionate a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, thought that he might come in and nick the time, with joining his Reaſons to thoſe of his Friend; he boldly came in, and taking one of his Siſters fair
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:66334:44"/>hands, he ſubtly laid it into St. <hi>Hubert's,</hi> who venturing to kiſs it with fervour, preſently ſought for the effect in her Eyes, which that Action might have produc'd, and finding nothing there that was ſiniſter to his love, he took the boldneſs to ſpeak to her of it as eloquently as he could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
               <p>Long ſince had Madamoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> known the Knight St. <hi>Hubert's</hi> paſſion, and her Heart had already given to it ſelf di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Leſſons on that Chapter; ſhe found nothing in it of advantage for her part; and ſetting aſide all his fine. Qualities, ſhe fretted at her ſelf, and at her ſmall riſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; Sometimes ſhe would flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her ſelf in her amorous thoughts, and her Brothers exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſeem'd to authoriſe her in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things. Thoſe Reflexions gave her but little reſt, and her
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66334:44"/>uneaſineſs did clearly appear on her face, ſhe had a Maid Servant, in whom ſhe did much confide, and who already was the confident of that pain which tormented her; ſhe made her to lie with her that night, and did conjure her to give her Remedies proper for her paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; how croſs is Love, <hi>ſaid ſhe ſighing,</hi> to kindle in two hearts ſo oppoſite in Religion, one and the ſame Love, ſo much agreement, with ſo much antipathy; then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe reaſons which ſhe thought to have to hate the Knight, ſhe would afterwards en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to juſtifie her inclinations, and let her ſelf be carry'd away by the rapid motion of her Star.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>La Grange,</hi> (ſo was that Maid nam'd,) who knew after what manner ſhe was to manage her Miſtreſſes mind, had never directly oppos'd her ſelf to her pleaſure,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:66334:45"/>not to affrighten her paſſion on the ſuddain, ſhe had contented her ſelf 'till then, to dexterouſly inſinuate to her, without affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſome hatred for all that was Catholick, and whether through that Motive, or for other ſecret Reaſons, ſhe never ceas'd ſpeaking well of St. <hi>Sauveur;</hi> yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that now her heart was on the point of determination, ſhe made her ſo powerful a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the evil conſequences which ſhe did foreſee, thereby to retard the courſe of a tenderneſs, which was taking a Road ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to her deſires, that at laſt ſhe did quite byaſs her. She ſaid that ſo ſtrong a paſſion could not be cur'd, but by violent Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; that to that effect, ſhe was to accuſtom her ſelf with ſome Gentleman worthy of her; that that was an eaſie way to deſtroy the Ideas of a primary flame, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:66334:45"/>that ſhe found nothing in St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> unworthy of her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem.</p>
               <p>Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> found both good ſence and ingenuity in that propoſition, and becoming melancholick in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, had almoſt no other thoughts than to free her ſelf from that evil which poſſeſs'd her: ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated her Brother to preſs her no longer on a thing ſo diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to her; ſhe let him ſee the difference there was betwixt an <hi>Hugonot</hi> who lov'd a Catholick Woman, and a Catholick who lov'd an <hi>Hugonot</hi> Woman; that his example ought not to perſwade her, nor to render her guilty of his weakneſſes. <hi>Chanlieu</hi> not knowing whence that blow came, was mov'd at this diſcourſe, and had not his Love taken him by his own intereſt, perhaps he had found thoſe reaſons of his Siſter
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:66334:46"/>very lawful; he then carp'd at all ſhe ſaid, and complain'd of it in a manner to make her appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how far his vexation did go.</p>
               <p>That was the Cauſe, why ſhe reſolv'd to uſe a great manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in her concerns, and to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſe: ſhe affected a gay hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and though reſolv'd never to ſacrifice her Conſcience's inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to that of her Love; ſhe did frequently give St. <hi>Hubert</hi> ſome little marks of that which ſhe had for him: this conſtraint did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely diſturb her Soul, and ſo rapid an agitation cauſing her to fall into a violent fever; there was for ſome days a doubt of her Cure; but at laſt youth, and her good habit did re-eſtabliſh her, almoſt againſt her own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
               <p>It can not be ſaid how much that ſickneſs caus'd of trouble to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:66334:46"/>St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> he himſelf had like to have died with ſorrow, while that St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> enrag'd to ſee, as it were in the arms of another, a Perſon whoſe Conqueſt he had thought ſo eaſie, did find ſome eaſe in his affliction, by that which his Rival did feel. He gave her a viſit, and having been inform'd that ſhe had ſpoke his name in the height of her raving, he the more preſſingly did expreſs to her the ſhare which he bore in her indiſpoſition. She receiv'd his Compliment in a very acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging manner, gave him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſhe approv'd of his viſit That Gentleman who did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſuch a favourable reception, return'd her a thouſand thanks, and went from her but with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, he could not gueſs whence that kind reception proceeded unleſs her Sickneſs had render'd her more tractable than formerly.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:66334:47"/>
               <p>It was about that time that St. <hi>Hubert</hi> had ſome information that his Kinſman the Viſcount was come into that Province, where he had conducted the Marchioneſs his Wife; his devoir inviting him to give them a Viſit; he learnt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his ſtay with them the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their miſunderſtanding. The Viſcount had formerly given a very rich Cabinet to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, in which the Workman had made a ſecret very difficult to be diſcover'd; and there remaining in it by accident a Billet-dous which he writ to her, ſhe after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture having examin'd every corner of the Cabinet, had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd the Bill to be deſign'd for ſome other, and being jealous of her ſelf, her paſſion had dictated that which he receiv'd in <hi>Lorain,</hi> ſo that at his return he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to avoid all future miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings by a ſudden Mariage,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:66334:47"/>and ſo conclude that to be only the means which could ſet him at eaſe. The Marchioneſs ſmil'd at the diſcourſe, and ſaid that if any one had taken advantage of her cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, that for the future ſhe would no longer paſs for ſimple, and that the Viſcount would take but too great advantages of her weakneſs: The Knight took de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in that little fuge, and gave them alſo an exact account of his late Adventures, how that he had found by chance, that which he could never find by any applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; with divers other paſſages of his Love. The Marchioneſs reſented a great deal of joy at it, and in the deſire to ſee a perſon that ſo much reſembled her, ſhe engag'd St. <hi>Hubert</hi> to afford her that ſatisfaction, ſo ſoon as ſhe ſhould be recover'd of her indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; ſhe enquired of him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he found himſelf Well of his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:66334:48"/>Love, and whether he believ'd not there were ſome Schiſm or Hereſie in the Service of a <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonot?</hi> on which he crav'd a ceſſation of Arms after a gallant manner; and made her a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and pleaſant Reverence, which ſtood in place of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partee.</p>
               <p>A Lover highly ſmitten can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make long diſcourſes in one and the ſame place, he ſtill bears ſomething in his mind that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs him, and deprives him of a great tranquility. Thus he had paſs'd whole Months at the Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, with that joy which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly the Marchioneſs did inſpire in him, on the likeneſs ſhe had with Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu:</hi> He had then conſolated himſelf of her abſence on ſo fair an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, had not the deſire which he had of knowing his Condition, continually perſecuted him: he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:66334:48"/>got on horſeback, and that very day came to her, where he found Madmoiſelle of St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> who was purpoſely come to take her friend in order to make her change air, and the Journey was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with <hi>Chanlieu</hi> againſt the next day.</p>
               <p>They were no ſooner come to his Houſe, but he particularly and wholly apply'd himſelf to procure them all the Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that the Seaſon would afford; he daily invented new ones, and being ſatisfied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himſelf to have ſo agreeable a Company, he fancy'd ſuch Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſco's, which he contriv'd in ſuch ſort, as made his wit to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd: Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> perceiv'd it but too much, and her heart which felt no real flame but for him, did endeavour to quench it by divers Leſſons which ſhe read to her ſelf; all her ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:66334:49"/>were very weak in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and if on the one hand ſhe had the vexation to love a Man, which could not marry her, on the other, ſhe found a particular Charm to behold and hear him which was capable to diſcover her ſecret. Love and Reaſon, gave by turns cruel onſets to her mind, and repreſenting to her ſelf fate more dangerous than it was, ſhe was very uneaſie. All endeavour'd to diſſipate that Melancholly, which ſeem'd as a relick of her Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And Madmoiſelle of St. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> having made her promiſe to be chearful, they reſolv'd to put a pleaſant trick upon the Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>He had writ to the Knight that he would come to ſee him. This laſt having ſancy'd that he might take Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> for his own Lady, he deſir'd <hi>Chanlieu</hi> to diſpoſe his Siſter to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:66334:49"/>take that day they ſhould come, ſuch an undreſs as the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs us'd to wear, ſhe eaſily conſented to it; the Viſcount came late with his Lady, and Saluted the whole Company, except Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> whom he really took for his own Lady; mean time fancying that he had ſeen her in two places at once, he remanin'd in a doubt, that gave occaſion to a fit of laughing, which diſcompos'd him. The Marchioneſs having firſt taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the miſtake, went and took Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> by the hand, made her a thouſand Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes on their reſemblance, and preſented her to her Husband; who, no longer doubting but ſhe was the Perſon of whom he had heard ſo much, Saluted her, and told her a hundred pleaſant things on that Subject: the time they were together having afforded
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:66334:50"/>divers agreeable Converſations, ſhe related to her the ſtory of het Bracelet, which ſhe promis'd to ſend to him.</p>
               <p>This Rencounter having ſtirr'd up a deſire in thoſe ingenious Perſons, of frequently ſeeing one another, they made Matches, from which Love, who gains from all things, gain'd advantage; and if the opening of the Campaign had not diſturb'd ſuch innocent plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, nothing had been wanting to their entire happineſs: The fair <hi>Chanlieu</hi> had no longer ſo great a weight of Melancholy, and Madmoiſelle of St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> who was naturally more airy, had ſo aptly inclin'd her mind towards pleaſures, that ſhe inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly did take delight to divert her ſelf as well as the reſt; ſhe had for ſome time committed the conduct of her Heart to her own deſtiny, and but weakly oppos'd
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:66334:50"/>her ſelf to the power of her paſſion: <hi>La Granges</hi> Counſels were fallen lame by the way, and St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> came no longer in Competition. Divertiſement would not allow her any time to think on her firſt Enterpriſe, and St. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> did eaſily find out opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities in which to expreſs his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs to her; but Orders being come, they were forc'd to part: <hi>Chanlieu</hi> would go a Volunteer to partake of thoſe dangers which might befall him; and this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, preceeded by a tender Farewel, drew a deluge of Tears, not excepting Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu.</hi> I muſt confeſs that St. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> told her the moſt moving things in the World; he did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulariſe to her the ſecret moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his paſſion, and omitted nothing to make her approve of ſo Heroick a Love. Muſt it be that through a diverſity of Faith <hi>(ſaid
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:66334:51"/>he)</hi> you ſhould refuſe to give me yours, which would render me moſt happy? believe me, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle, the Orders of the Court ſhall never make me to act any thing to your preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice: You ſhall ever be the Miſtreſs of my Heart, and I ſhall ſacrifice with pleaſure my Fortune to my Love. Then would he change Diſcourſe, to inform her after what manner they might Love without agreeing in their Religions; he ſeem'd by theſe Arguments to ſet both their Hearts in a perfect harmony, and that nothing could oppoſe it; he offer'd at making ſome agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as to the difference of their Belief, but ſhe for her part un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to venture any thing of that nature, called him a Love Caſuiſt, ſhe told him that he look'd on their difference in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, but by the moſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:66334:51"/>Light, and that he ſpoke but by halves concerning their difficulties: Yes, Knight, I ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect you, <hi>added ſhe,</hi> and If I diſtruſt my ſelf in Love, why may not I ſuſpect you? I inſiſt not to obtain a Victory, which perhaps might coſt me my Life. Remember, that it would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice many others if I did but meerly aſſure them of my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and that I wiſh you an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py return. He could obtain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than the permiſſion of Writing to her, when Monſieur of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> would inform him of her Health, and taking leave of her, they went their ways with the Viſcount, all three poſſeſs'd with very different thoughts.</p>
               <p>Monſieur the Marſhal of <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui,</hi> was very eager to recover that credit by the taking of <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburg,</hi> which he had loſt through the great Snow that had fallen
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:66334:52"/>the Year before, and to reduce a place which he had been in a manner oblig'd to quit. All the Winter had been employ'd about all the neceſſary Preparations, to beat back Parties that continually Sally'd out on the Plains; the Orders were given from Court, and the Approaches were made with more eaſe than was expected; the Trench was open'd, and the Prince of <hi>Chymai</hi> omitting nothing on his part, for the preſervation of a Town which he was reſolv'd to defend for divers Reaſons, both Parties diſpos'd themſelves to a vigorous offence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. The Governour, that he might not tax himſelf of any neglect, fail'd not in the leaſt to any Duty of his function, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding policy to ſtrength, caus'd in one Night all his Batteries to be rais'd, on certain elevations which command a great Plain; and the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:66334:52"/>next day he ſent ſome Squadrons to ſhew themſelves on that ſide; the Beſiegers who went to Charge them, ſent their Horſe after them, but the <hi>Spaniards</hi> giving way too ſoon, there was not had from the fire of the Batteries all the ſucceſs, which had been expected. Yet St. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> who had been Commanded one of the firſt, to beat back that Party, was wounded with a ſplinter in the Head, and though his Wound did not appear very dangerous, it caus'd him a very violent Fever, which put his Friend into ſome fears.</p>
               <p>He writ word of it to his Siſter, who during their long abſence had lieſure to abandon her ſelf to her auſtere Reflections: <hi>La Grange,</hi> who found thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments favourable to her deſires, did inceſſantly labour in them, and St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> was on his part
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:66334:53"/>very aſſiduous, in expreſſing to her after a nice manner ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Paſſion. This Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Maiden aſſaulted ſo many ways, did reſiſt as much as ſhe could poſſibly, and Love would ſoon make her to return from all that ſhe undertook to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice. How happy am I, <hi>ſaid ſhe one day, in the heighth of her thoughts,</hi> to ſtill diſpair following that Party, which Reaſon and my Duty lead me to, and that a fatal Love ſhould come unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to triumph over my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! no, continued ſhe, I muſt triumph in my turn, and after I have ſo long ſuffer'd, I will take up a reſolution, advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to my Conſcience, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to my Tenderneſs: My Heart which firſt yielded, ſhall be the firſt Victim which I will ſacrifice to my ſeverity, and St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> ſhall poſſeſs that place, which I
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:66334:53"/>had too weakly given up to a Catholick.</p>
               <p>This laſt thought had ſo prevail'd over her mind, that ſhe omitted no means of finding opportunities to favour St. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> and to give him marks of a tenderneſs, which ſhe endeavour'd to raviſh from St. <hi>Hubert:</hi> He was privately ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertis'd of it by his correſpondent; and if he had not made and amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſcruple of accepting of an Heart which was not offer'd him by a Principle of Inclination, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure that he had wholly triumph'd over his Rival, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Indifferency which was had for him: He therefore complain'd of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner after which he was to be belov'd, and refining on the ſcore of ſenſibility, he proteſted to her that he preferr'd hatred to ſuch a kind of Love, that he had ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died on the nature of tenderneſs,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:66334:54"/>and that he figur'd to himſelf no pleaſure but in a conformity of Sentiments.</p>
               <p>This generous proceeding was capable of increaſing that eſteem which ſhe might have for him; Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering to him that which ſhe felt for St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> did on the other hand aſſure him, that it was not only through neceſſity, that ſhe had reſolv'd to receive him fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably; that friendſhip uſually was a fore-runner of Love, and that in a word he fram'd to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>Chimeras</hi> on a Party which he ought to embrace with joy; that ſhe would cure her ſelf in time of a flame, which ſhe look'd on already as guilty, and that he ought not to diſtruſt his own good Parts. In all that, there was nothing but what was very obliging, and St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> had doubtleſs paſs'd over all conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:66334:54"/>if there had been any bottom in all thoſe advances which were made him: Madmoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> ſtill wavering in her deſigns, wiſh'd her ſelf ill for having made him ſuch large ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and the Idea of the Knight appearing again to her Eyes with all his Charms, ſhe retracted in her ſelf thoſe Offers which ſhe had made in favour of his Rival. The news alſo of his illneſs came ſo pat to diſturb that new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that one ſcarcely can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the effect which it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd: Compaſſion brought back her true Love, and made her then, more than ever, to know the true Character of her Paſſion.</p>
               <p>She was oppreſs'd with fear, and apprehending the danger greater than it was, her Soul was plung'd into inconceivable trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and agitations: She would ſometimes repreſent to her ſelf
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:66334:55"/>the Knight half dead; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times again ſhe would check that thought which ſhe had entertain'd of driving him from a place which ſo juſtly poſſeſs'd: She render'd a Viſit to Madmoiſelle of St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> to ſhew her what part ſhe took in that ſorrow which that ill News did cauſe her, and reſolv'd not to leave her very ſoon, ſhe gave Orders to keep that Viſit private, that ſhe might not be diſturb'd. They related to one another very agreeable things on the conformity of their Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; they exclam'd againſt that blindneſs of Fate, that had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd ſuch croſs oppoſitions in their Amours, in managing ſo ill their Inclinations; they both ſtorm'd againſt the rigour of the Edicts, and a Thouſand times wiſh'd to have them re-eſtabliſh'd in the ſame condition in which <hi>Henry</hi> the Great had left them.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:66334:55"/>
               <p>Finally, after having expreſs'd great Complaints, they thought they ought to temporiſe a little, and that peradventure time would produce then ſome unexpected means; that it were better to wait patiently for the time to come, than to torment them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves through uncertain apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. That was the beſt part they had to take; it is to languiſh to be always foreſeing what is to happen either of pleaſant or diſtaſtful; the privation of a Good which we hope for, paſſes in our minds for a real loſs, and it is but the forwarding of ones evil, thus to ſeek after it before it be come. St. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> could not tell ſince that time to what to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute that coldneſs which he found in Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu's</hi> proceeding; and though he valued himſelf on the account of Penetration, yet could he not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:66334:56"/>diſcover the true cauſe thereof. All that <hi>La Grange</hi> could ſay, was, that it was an effect of her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs's Irreſolution; he would not believe it, and boggling at all things, he fruitleſly ſought after that which was ſo eaſie to be found; his hopes being ſo ſoon vaniſh'd away did much afflict him, and meeting, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his new Attempts, with a reſiſtance which he had not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, his Reſentment prevail'd above his Reaſon, and vex'd to have been the Cully of a Woman, he reſolv'd to have no conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for a Perſon who had ſo little regard for him.</p>
               <p>There is nothing ſo dangerous as a Lover, who thinks himſelf play'd upon by that Perſon of whom he is favour'd; his Love frequently degenerates into fury, and nothing is capable to put a ſtop to his fatal deſigns. St. <hi>Sauveur</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:66334:56"/>reſenting a wrong which he look'd on as the higheſt of ſcorn, prepoſſeſs'd on the other hand with his good Qualities, paſs'd on the ſudden into extravagancies, and reſolv'd to revenge himſelf, at any rate ſoever. He remember'd that an <hi>Italian</hi> had frequently mention'd to him a compos'd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume, which might eaſily. be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd in a Packet of Letters, and which at the very firſt opening would attack with his ſuttle and corroſive parts, whatſoever offer'd it ſelf to them.</p>
               <p>He was not ignorant how jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a young Lady is of her Beauty, and that treachery ſeem'd to him proper for his revenge, he was reſolv'd to make uſe of it, to puniſh that which he call'd the infidelity of a Demon, in Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu;</hi> it was her Face that had firſt of all poiſon'd his Heart, he thought
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:66334:57"/>by that, his Enterpriſe to be Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoris'd, and that after he ſhould have deſtroy'd her Charms, he ſhould eaſily compaſs the reſt; that the Cauſe once ceaſing, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects would ceaſe alſo, and that ſhe ſhould have leiſure to repent of the wrong which ſhe had done him. He went his way in that cruel reſolution, to find out his Man at <hi>Paris,</hi> and to ſet him to work about that inſtrument of his Revenge.</p>
               <p>Without diſpute, Love fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently produces ſtrange Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſes, and if it is a fine thing in it ſelf, he yet ſometimes begets Monſters. St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> had always paſs'd for a brave and good Man, incapable of an ill Action, and ſome little vanity which he naturally had, did not hinder but that he had acquir'd the Reputation and Eſteem of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Men. Mean time his Paſſion
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:66334:57"/>having ſeiz'd his Brain, he fanſied that he had right to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of an unconſtancy, and his deſpiſed flame continually offering it ſelf to his Eyes, he reſolv'd in that infatuation, to ſatisfy himſelf at the coſt of his Honour and Conſcience. So ſoon as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume was finiſh'd, he firſt made a trial of it on a Wretch, ſo that being aſſur'd of the Succeſs, he got the <hi>Italian</hi> to make up the Packet, which he himſelf ſealed with a counterfeit Cypher of St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> in opinion that the Letter would therefore be open'd with more eagerneſs, and being return'd home, he gave order to have it ſent to the <hi>Poſt-houſe;</hi> after which, being fill'd with black me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Thoughts, he abſtain'd from ſeeing her, for fear her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſhould make him to alter his deſign, and went out of a Kingdom where his Conſcience
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:66334:58"/>began to be tormented on divers accounts.</p>
               <p>It will be ſomething ſurpriſing, to hear that a Perſon capable of ſo much baſeneſs, ſhould quit his Country on a Principle of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but whether through that motive, or through ſome other, it is ſtill certain that he retir'd into <hi>Holland,</hi> where he had great Acquaintances, perhaps it was alſo, that he would abſent himſelf from a place, where he had been put to ſuch Trials, and not to be near a Perſon that he treated ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely. He left a Servant behind him, in whom he put great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, to give him an account of that Buſineſs, and ſtole away, not taking leave of any body. Divers Perſons were ſurpriz'd at his diſappearing, and Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> not knowing where to attribute this Retreat poſitively, believ'd that an amorous diſguſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:66334:58"/>might have call'd him to <hi>Paris</hi> to ſeek after other Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he having taken that Road to bring him at the <hi>Hague</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He could ſcarce ſeek after a Retreat more agreeable, and more proper to divert his melancholy Thoughts, both by its curious Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, and the fine People which uſually meet at the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range's,</hi> who then was ſeeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the means imaginable to put a ſtop to the King's Progreſs, which were publickly term'd an Invaſion, and an infraction of the laſt Treaties at <hi>Nimeguen;</hi> but Alas! the more he ſought to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert himſelf, the leſs he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a condition to reliſh the leaſt Divertiſement; his late Action did continually preſent it ſelf to his Mind, and his Rage having given ſome place to Reaſon, he reſented a torment which afforded
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:66334:59"/>him no reſt. In this mortal reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs, he learnt by his Man's arrival the miſchief which his Perfume had caus'd, in taking away Madamoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi>'s Life with her Beauty; that that Tragedy had ſurpriz'd divers Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that at the firſt noiſe of it he had haſtned to join him at the Rendevous. Never was Man more deeply ſtruck than he was at that Relation, he fell into a kind of a Swound, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd him of his Senſes, and at laſt coming to himſelf again, he continued making of reproaches to himſelf that mov'd compaſſion; he twenty times call'd himſelf the Executioner of the faireſt Perſon in the World; and paſſing from invectives to a giddineſs, he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly felt a ſorrow which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd him. So many ſufferings did at laſt alter his Health; he fell into a languidneſs, that was
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:66334:59"/>accompanied with an exceſſive Feaver, whence he hop'd to receive a perfect Cure.</p>
               <p>Mean time, his Man had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd himſelf in the relation which he had made him, and that noiſe which had been made of the Death of Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu,</hi> had been found falſe. <hi>La Grange,</hi> who was St. <hi>Sauveur</hi>'s Creature, and who improv'd by his Liberality, having been the firſt that receiv'd that Packet, did not doubt examining the Seal, but that it came from St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> ſhe imagin'd that ſhe ſhould do a ſingular piece of Service to St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> to ſuppreſs it, and make him partaker of its Contents; ſhe open'd it then with great earneſtneſs, and the Poiſon eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porating at that inſtant, made preſently a paſſage for it ſelf through the Mouth on to the Heart, ſhe made a great out-cry,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:66334:60"/>which made ſome Perſons run to her, but nothing could preſerve her from a ſudden Death.</p>
               <p>No body did imagine that her illneſs proceeded from that Paper, which was not ſo much as minded, nor the Author capable of ſuch a Crime; it was rather attributed to thoſe ſudden Accidents, which ſometimes happen when the leaſt thought on. Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> was ſorry at it, and nothing leſs than the return of two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo dear to her could diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate her grief: St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> and <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> came very opportunely for her, and ſhe being reſolv'd to follow her own tendency, ſhe thought thenceforth to profit by thoſe Leſſons, which Love had made her during their abſence. In effect, to what purpoſe thus ſo obſtinately to oppoſe our ſelves to our deſires? The Remedies we ſeek after do but increaſe our pain,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:66334:60"/>and in Love alone is to be found a Cure for Love; all Preſervatives are uſeleſs, we ſeem to triumph over it for a time, but only to render our weakneſs more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious. This was the Condition in which was her heart, and St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> who knew what Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rective ſhe made uſe of, did ſo well play his batteries that way, that he never ſhot at random; he ſet himſelf up for a Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mender of both the Religions, and dexterouſly applying thoſe ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which Monſieur of <hi>Condom</hi> has made uſe of to delude the Reformed, he had perhaps led her into ſome of thoſe kind of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls, if ſhe had had leſs of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning, and of fortitude.</p>
               <p>The Edicts, and the King's new Declarations did then cauſe an infinite number of innocent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſhed tears, and forc'd a great number to flye from a
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:66334:61"/>Countrey where their minds were kept under ſuch a ſevere ſlavery. Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> did ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly diſingage her ſelf from thoſe falſe ſhadows which Love us'd to lull her Conſcience aſleep, that ſhe vow'd to follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of ſo many generous Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives, and to abandon her own Countrey.</p>
               <p>The Paſſages began to be poſſeſs'd, ſince the Squabbles of the Province of <hi>Daulphine,</hi> and ſhe had gladly made uſe of St. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> to facilitate her retreat, if it had been poſſible; his Crime was ſtill unknown to her, and ſhe had eaſily intruſted her ſelf to his Cares and Conduct.</p>
               <p>She openly chid her Brother on his ſluggiſhneſs, and told him things grounded on ſo firm and Chriſtian a Moral, that perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture he had reſolv'd not to be, of the number of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſers,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:66334:61"/>if he had leſs permitted himſelf to be poſſeſs'd with his paſſion. In this confuſion ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd that ſhe might obtain one thing from her Lover's Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, after which ſhe ſigh't with ſo much ardency, his merit was not unknown to her, and in the hopes of receiving from him that mark of a truly Heroick Love, on which ſhe ſhould account all her life time, ſhe reſolv'd to propoſe it to him at the firſt opportunity; and beginning, by letting him ſee in her lovely eyes, and in her actions, ſome part of her tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; How unjuſt and capricious is Fate, ſaid ſhe to him, to that purpoſe? I find in my ſelf ſome diſpoſitions to love you, which cauſe me to bluſh, and if my whole Religion did not ſtep in to my aid, perhaps you would not complain of my ſeverity: But, Knight, judge without Intereſt,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:66334:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:66334:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:66334:63"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:66334:63"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:66334:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:66334:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:66334:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:66334:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:66334:66"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:66334:66"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:66334:67"/>of the Party which is left me to take; or rather acknowledge your ſelf, that you would be ſorry to ſee a thing happen, which would coſt me no leſs than my life. I could wiſh in a word, that our Religions could agree together as well as our hearts: Alas! you ſhould not then reproach me of Inſenſibility. There ſhe ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of tears, which had like to have made St. <hi>Hubert</hi> die with Love; he cleav'd to her knees, and endeavouring to gather on his face ſome of that precious water, he told her languiſhingly, that he ſhould make to himſelf perpetual reproaches to have lov'd her, if his Love was not of a different Character from that of other men; and if he did not diſtinguiſh that bright flame which kindled it. Yes, Madmoiſelle, anſwer'd he to her, I love you like a Goddeſs, and your Orders are ſo dear to me,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:66334:67"/>that it ſhall never be ſaid that I have refus'd punctually to put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution what-ever you ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me. I am ready to ſacrifice to you my Intereſts, and my Life, and after thoſe ſoft words I have newly heard, I cannot dye unhappy.</p>
               <p>Alas! anſwer'd ſhe, I never doubted of the brightneſs of your flame; I know you but too much, Knight, and perhaps I ſhould not know you ſo much, but this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of the Court diſconſolates me; and ſeeing I muſt begin to give you ſome marks of my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by that of my confidence, I am forc'd to confeſs to you, that nothing ties me more to my own Country, than the pleaſure I have to ſee you there; and that my Conſcience inceſſantly preſſing me on that point, I cannot defer going elſe-where to ſeek out a ſafe place of refuge for it. You ſigh, <hi>added ſhe,</hi> but do you not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:66334:68"/>find, that it is better yet, that I ſhould live abſent from you, than to expire with grief and ſorrow; yet there is no medium, thoſe two extremities are Infallible; and if my flight ſaves me not from the danger I am in, nothing elſe but death can free me from it. Think of it, St. <hi>Hubert, continu'd ſhe,</hi> you alone can ſave me, and if the Heavens do ever re-unite us again, I do promiſe you that it ſhall be by that obligation accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany'd with all my tenderneſs, that I ſhall begin to crown your flame.</p>
               <p>This Lover caſt down in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, through his Love, and his Virtue, knew not how to reſolve himſelf to become the inſtrument of his own misfortune, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conceiv'd her intention, and reflecting on the oddneſs of his Fate, he was a long time conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering in himſelf, without ſaying
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:66334:68"/>a word, their Souls ſaw one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through their eyes, and he finally broke ſilence by an anſwer interrupted with ſighs; I ſhould amuſe my ſelf, to ſeek for Succour in a long reaſoning, ſaid he, to remove from you a thought, which directly oppoſes the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of my Love, and I ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make you quit a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſo fatal to my quiet, if I did not know the ſtedfaſtneſs of your reſolutions. I know, Madmoiſelle, that you will always do what you will by invincible reaſonings; I even know that you will find in my blindful obedience more of Ardency and Paſſion, than of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, that you will attribute to the greatneſs of my flame, that ſubmiſſion for every thing that comes from your deſires. But, Madmoiſelle, have you conſider'd well of it? And ſhould we not both do better to take ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:66334:69"/>time to run over this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize? No, added he, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle, I am overcome, and though it ſhould coſt me ten thouſand Lives, I will ſacrifice them to you, and deprive my ſelf of a good that I ſhould prefer to all the bleſſings of the World. He ended theſe words with ſo moving an air, that ſhe had much to do to refrain expreſſing her Reſentments to him by ſuch Careſſes as had been full of innocency. Ah! Love, Love, how unjuſtly doſt thou treat us, (they both cry'd out,) and having tenderly preſs'd each others hands, they parted with ſorrow painted on their faces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> having ſuſpected ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Siſter's Deſign, found himſelf in a great confuſion; he went to ſee St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> who made out the buſineſs to him, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to his particular intereſt, that he might perſwade him to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:66334:69"/>divert that enterprize, he told him in that view, that there might be ſome intelligence betwixt his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and St. <hi>Sauveur;</hi> that his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement render'd the thing but too likely, that at leaſt, it was neceſſary, firſt, to be well inform'd of it, before they proceeded any further. But St. <hi>Hubert</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by this Diſcourſe, that Love only could be capable of ſuch a reaſoning, anſwer'd him, that he was aſſur'd of his Siſter's right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and that far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that any other had any place in her heart, he did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair one day to poſſeſs her wholly himſelf; proteſted to him at the ſame time, that no diſtance ſhould be in the leaſt prejudicial to his Love; that on the contrary, he ſhould ſeek more than ever after his friendſhip, in this abſence.</p>
               <p>This aſſurance having ſet <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> in his right temper again, he
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:66334:70"/>return'd home, to diſcourſe with his Siſter about it, and to let her know, that he ſhould follow her ſo ſoon as he had ſet his Concerns in the beſt order he could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. He effectually began it, in drawing conſiderable Bills of Exchange for her, upon a Rich Banker of <hi>London;</hi> and not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to accompany her far, to avoid all ſuſpicions, ſhe took the Road to <hi>Paris,</hi> where St. <hi>Hubert</hi> waited for her.</p>
               <p>She afterwards went from thence, habited like a young Engliſh Lord, with him and a Woman, whom ſhe had oblig'd alſo to put on a Man's Apparel: His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was at <hi>Calis,</hi> and the Packet-Boat being ready the next day after they came he gain'd ſome Fiſher-men to carry that precious truſt to that Engliſh Veſſel, ſo ſoon as it ſhould be a League at Sea. The hour of parting being
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:66334:70"/>come, it may be ſaid that there did then paſs betwixt thoſe two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons the moſt tender farewel in the world. Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> did find ſo many charms in that laſt action, that ſhe thought her ſelf not oblig'd to obſerve much Decorum: ſhe aſſur'd him, that that ſeparation did increaſe that eſteem ſhe had for him, and that the Fates would one day find a Secret to re-unite them more cloſely; tears after that were ſhed on both ſides, and ſhe being got into their Veſſel with her Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the Knight return'd home uncapable to conceal his ſorrow.</p>
               <p>He paſs'd a very ill night, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain as he was of his Deſtiny, he complain'd againſt his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, then finding nothing in it but what was generous, he concluded that Love ought to have treated him with more mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and indulgency. By break
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:66334:71"/>of day he ſent for one of the Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-men, and having learnt that they had ſucceſsfully put the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies on board the Packet-Boat, he was leſs uneaſie, and better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. But that Tranquillity laſted not long, and that beginning was follow'd with a very Tragical concluſion. He frequently did go to the Sea-ſhore, as if to ask what news of his Miſtreſs; and ſome days being paſs'd in an unparallel'd expectation of Letters; news was brought by another Packet-Boat, that the firſt had wrack'd againſt an <hi>Hollander,</hi> and that the ſtorm was ſo high, that they had not fav'd ſo much as the Crew. He had this Fatal and Sorrowful Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture repeated five or ſix times over, and fearing publickly to diſcover a grief which might have betray'd his Secret, he went and melted into tears in his Cloſet.</p>
               <p>Nothing could conſolate him,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:66334:71"/>and that loſs appear'd ſo ſenſible to him, that he ſoon found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a Condition worthy of Compaſſion; he reproach'd to himſelf to have been the cauſe (through his blind complacency) of the death of a Perſon whom he ſo tenderly lov'd; ſometimes he not only deſir'd death, but in that moment he would have ſought after it with honour; he would ſtill return on the Shore, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach that Mercileſs Element of its great injuſtice, and to demand of it at leaſt that body which it was unworthy to contain. He would ſeek about for ſome pieces of the wrack, and he abandon'd himſelf to a Sorrow that was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to kill him.</p>
               <p>An Officer of <hi>Fuſtenberg,</hi> who had his Chamber near to his, and who had heard him complain in private, miſtruſted ſomething of his ill fortune, and took the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:66334:72"/>to ſpeak to him of it; he at firſt feign'd to have formerly had ſuch a misfortune as his, that what he ſhould ſay to him, might make a ſtronger impreſſion on his mind. He added, that peradventure ſhe might have eſcap'd from periſhing, that the thing was not impoſſible, and that he ſhould not do ill to take a turn in <hi>Holland</hi> to inform himſelf exactly of it. That Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition pleas'd the Knight, and this Officer having had leave to go to <hi>Denmark,</hi> whence he was, he offer'd to accompany him; ſo that they went down the River <hi>Eſcaut,</hi> and viſited all the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of thoſe Provinces, till at laſt he believ'd he might hear more fully at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> (where they parted) the particulars of that Shipwrack, which pierc'd his heart.</p>
               <p>His reſtleſneſs ſcarce affording him any reſt: he continually
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:66334:72"/>walk'd in the great places of that Town; he would frequently go ſo far as the <hi>Texell,</hi> to know whether the Veſſel which had caus'd the Packet-Boat to miſcarry, was not return'd; he put all the Seamen he met with on that Theme, and the uncertainty that every body was in about that Veſſel, ſerv'd but to increaſe his Sorrow, and ſend him home with an addition of Grief. One day as he paſs'd through the Quarters of the <hi>Jews,</hi> he was ſtop'd there by an Object which ſurpriz'd him; and in the dread of finding in it the certainty of his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, nothing but his deſpair could oblige him, as it were againſt his will to draw nearer to it; it was a Woman's habit, which he knew but too well for that of his unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Miſtreſs; he became mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionleſs at the ſight of a thing that depriv'd him of all the reſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:66334:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:66334:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:66334:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:66334:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:66334:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:66334:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:66334:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:66334:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:66334:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:66334:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:66334:78"/>of his hopes; he had not the power to ſpeak for a while, his Soul being at laſt return'd from its wandering, he look't on thoſe ſad Relicks in the moſt ſad and moſt moving manner imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; he ask'd the price of it, and enquir'd of the <hi>Jew</hi> how he had come by it?</p>
               <p>It was by the means of a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence at <hi>Roan,</hi> by whom he frequently receiv'd old Cloaths. The wracks of the Packet-Boat, which had been driven to ſhore, had been found by Souldiers, who had kept them, but ſo long time as requir'd to ſell them; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an exact ſearch was made after all that had been found, they had rid themſelves of it ſo faſt as they could. The Knight thus inform'd, pay'd for the Suit, and had it carried to his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where he water'd it with a torrent of tears. He complain'd
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:66334:78"/>of his ill ſate in ſo moving an air, that no body could forbear to Sympathiſe with him in his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; he was laid in a Bed over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with grief, and in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that mov'd compaſſion; he at firſt refus'd all ſort of nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but at laſt he took a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution worthy of his Courage; for in the thoughts that the Sea might have caſt on Shoar the Body of a Perſon ſo dear to him, he reſolv'd to examine all the Coaſts adjacent to the wrack, to enquire after a thing which appear'd ſo important to his Love; he got to the <hi>Hague,</hi> where he was oblig'd to reſt two days, to repair the troubles of his mind; but reſt did but increaſe his reſtleſneſs; he found in all places the Perſon he hunted after, and Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> did continually appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, his imagination would make him divers repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Shipwrack; which
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:66334:79"/>griev'd him ſo, that ſome times, believing himſelf preſent at that accident, he would frequently riſe on the ſudden, as if to aſſiſt her whom he thought to ſee in the midſt of the waves.</p>
               <p>In the heighth of theſe his ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, there happen'd an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in his Inn, which ſerv'd but to confound him the more; St. <hi>Sauveur</hi> had lodg'd there, during his ſtay in that Town; and the Knight's appartment had been his. He had taken Ship to go for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> overcome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> remorces, and the negligence of his Man, who had let him forget ſome looſe Papers in the corner of a Chamber, behind the Hangings, gave opportunity to St. <hi>Hubert</hi>'s Man to lay his hands on them; amongſt which, he found a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which he gave to his Maſter; it was a deſcription of St. <hi>Sauveur</hi>'s Love, his Purſuits, and his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Effects; he there impos'd
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:66334:79"/>on himſelf moſt grievous torments, and ſevere puniſhments; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd that being unworthy to live after ſo barbarous an action, he deſign'd to end the reſt of his days, in the bottom of ſome hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and diſmal Wilderneſs; that to begin the puniſhment of his Crime, he would Publiſh it, and by that means, make ſome kind of reparation to a Perſon whom he had treated with ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity; the Letter was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out direction, and concluded with an Eternal farewel, and aſſurances, that he was going to end the reſt of his days in ſome hollow Cave in the Iſle of <hi>Carolina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Knight was not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he found the ſence to this Letter, which was deſign'd for <hi>La Grange,</hi> on whom all the ill fate of that Enterprize had fallen; he doubted not but that this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Lover was the Author of a death which had made ſome
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:66334:80"/>noiſe, and that he had attempted on a Perſon, whoſe loſs had ſo ſoon follow'd his pernicious practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. He ſixt himſelf after the manner of the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> to ſeek for her Body, to render his laſt Duties to thoſe Relicks which he ador'd; and following his way, he made the moſt exact perqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition after it that could be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd.</p>
               <p>When he was got at <hi>Roan,</hi> he learnt, that not long ſince five or ſix dead Bodies had been taken up in the <hi>Downs,</hi> and particularly that of a Woman, who doubtleſs was a Perſon of Quality, by thoſe Jewels which had been ſound in the ſolds of her Cloathes. That News accompliſh'd his deſpair; he did intreat of the Commander that he might take her up again to make a Funeral worthy of her; and his Love inſpiring him with Thoughts full of diſtraction, did retain him long in a place
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:66334:80"/>which was ſo grievious to him, ſo that he had much to do to get from it to return home.</p>
               <p>Madmoiſelle of St. <hi>Hubert</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently perceiv'd that there was ſomething more than abſence in his Mind, and his Tears having made her to hit on the right cauſe, ſhe made loud Complaints, which oblig'd <hi>Chanlieu</hi> to come and take his ſhare, in the cruel deſtiny of a Perſon that was ſo dear to them all.</p>
               <p>The Knight in the midſt of ſo many Condolances, believ'd that he ſhould better and with more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience bear with his ſorrow in ſuch places where he had never ſeen his charming Miſtreſs, and the King ſending then ſome ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> againſt the Inhabitants of the Vallies, whom he accus'd to have given protection to his Fugitive Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, he was of the number of thoſe Officers that were Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:66334:81"/>for that Expedition: His departure was no longer accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with thoſe troubles which are caus'd by ſeparation from a Miſtreſs; he had then ſuch as were much more grievous to bear, and the ſweet hopes to ſee again what one loves had no place in his Breaſt. He at every moment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to himſelf Madamoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> dead and buried, and the ſatisfaction of that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance did but increaſe his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. In that conflict of Thoughts, there happen'd one very ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which was that he believ'd, in going to make his Campaign the Ghoſt of that illuſtrious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would reproach his Conduct, and would blame him for having made War againſt Perſons that were of her Religion.</p>
               <p>That conſideration did ſtay him in the Province of <hi>Dauphine;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides he being not over much prepoſſeſt with the Opinions of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:66334:81"/>the Catholicks, he found that they acted with too much ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour againſt innocent Perſons, which were charged with imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Crimes. That Languidneſs which he had contracted, furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with means to feign an Indiſpoſition, he obtain'd to be tranſported to <hi>Grenoble</hi> to recover his Health; where having not found the Air conformable to his melancholy humour, he afterwards choſe <hi>Marfeilles,</hi> the Governour of which place he particularly knew; and finding that Sea-port to his mind, he reſolv'd to reſide there.</p>
               <p>His particular delight was the walk on the Key, where at every hour there are ſeen Ships come in loaded with Curioſities. Beſides, he impos'd it as a Law to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to frequently reproach the Sea of her unjuſtice, and to ask it an account of the Murther
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:66334:82"/>which it had committed; he never did ſee any ſtrange Veſſels come in, but he inform'd himſelf of the Road they had come, and that which they deſign'd to keep, and preferring that Diverſion to all thoſe which others would have procur'd him, he would ſtay in the Citadel no longer time than needed, not to appear ridiculous.</p>
               <p>The Governour, who thought himſelf oblig'd to Divert him, omitted nothing to that purpoſe, wherefore he made Matches in conſideration of him. And the pleaſure which the Knight took to be on Ship-board, having obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Governour to invite him one day at Dinner on one of the largeſt that was in the Harbour; he was interrupted by an Officer, who gave him notice, that one of the Viſitors had found ſome Proteſtant Subjects on a <hi>Dutch</hi> Veſſel, which the Storm had forc'd in. That news was unpleaſing
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:66334:82"/>to him, but the Orders of the Court being very preciſe on that account, he order'd that they ſhould be preſently brought to him: But how great was St. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>'s ſurpriſe at their coming! he thought he ſaw amongſt them Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu;</hi> and taking for a fantaſm, what doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs was a real Body, he fancied himſelf to be in an Inchanted Iſland, or that at leaſt this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture was nothing but a Dream. His Heart was in a continual throbbing, and in that uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of his good fortune, he knew not what Party to take. His Eyes were ſo wild, and his Thoughts ſo confus'd, that he ſcarce knew himſelf; yet he found himſelf no longer liable to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes; his Love had taught him the difference there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt her and all the reſt of the World, and the Viſcounteſs could no longer make him miſtake.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:66334:83"/>He drew near to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who knew all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, to offer to him his doubt, at that very moment that he was throughly inform'd by a look full of Reproaches: He preſently run to ask her pardon for his tardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and having inform'd her of the Reaſons, he continu'd to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to her a joy full of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports.</p>
               <p>The preſence of ſo many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons could not but be troubleſome to two reviv'd Lovers. The Governour left them alone, to taſte with leſs conſtraint the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a faithful and tender Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; during ſome time they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd themſelves, but with a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, in which they confounded their looks: They a thouſand times interrupted one another with Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions; St. <hi>Hubert</hi> caſt himſelf at her Feet, as to return her thanks that he found her alive again, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had no longer doubted of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:66334:83"/>her Death. He would ask her, whether it was really her ſelf, or whether it was her ſhadow only that was come to comfort him for her loſs; he anew did cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteriſe to her the moſt tender parts of his Love; and having much to do to expreſs himſelf in ſo happy a juncture, he gave her time to make this following Relation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You know,</hi> Knight, <hi>to what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our ſeparation did reduce me, and how troubled my Soul was at our parting, I felt it yet more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly than I expreſs'd it; and if I had not flatter'd my ſelf of ſeeing you again one day, perhaps my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize had fallen ſhort, and I had gone no farther. Ah!</hi> Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle, interrupted <hi>St.</hi> Hubert, <hi>that is too much for me, or rather it is ſufficient to make me die for Love; I bleſs my Fate,</hi> added he, kiſſing moſt paſſionately her Hand, <hi>and I no longer doubt, after I have found you again, but that the Heavens will
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:66334:84"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:66334:84"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:66334:85"/>remove all obſtacles which are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to my entire felicity.</hi> Then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to examine, whether there was not ſome illuſion in what that day had produc'd of ſuch a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuious nature, he ſhew'd by his Actions a flame moſt pure and moſt violent. <hi>Happen what will,</hi> he would ſay again with paſſion, <hi>after I have believ'd you dead, Love has preſerv'd my Life, but to live happy for the future, and my bliſs is to be envied.</hi> He had gone on in his Tranſports, if ſhe had not let him know, that ſhe would end her Narrative while they were alone, and that his Love was for a time to give place to his attention.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I had ſome fore-knowledge of my misfortune,</hi> continued ſhe, <hi>by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Circumſtances which preceded it, and which began to make me find the difference of the two Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Thoſe Fiſher-men to whom you had intruſted me, did not appear to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:66334:85"/>me made like other Men; they had in their looks ſomething of roughneſs, which made me to fear ſome ill deſign; neither did they fail of improving the occaſion which had been offer'd them, and their terrible barbarous nature inclining them to caſt us into the Sea, it was a miracle that they were ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd with our Money only, with threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to kill us, or to deliver us into the Inquiſitors hands. I had by chance caus'd my Jewels to be ſew'd up in the folds of my Cloaths, which I had made the Maid that ſerv'd me to put on, and which by that means were ſav'd from the plunder. Theſe Pirates having put us on board the Paſſage-boat, I felt ſome inconveniences, which, join'd to my ſorrow, took almoſt all manner of knowledge from me: The Sea, and the agitation of the Waves having made me ſuffer much, I was not in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to obſerve what happen'd after. I only remember, that after I had heard great ſhrieks and outcries, I fell into a deep Swoon, which hindred
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:66334:86"/>me from ſeeing that evil which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to us: I at laſt found my ſelf in a little Bed, ſerv'd by a Man who was not unknown to me; and caſting about my wild looks, I had not the power to ask neither where I was, nor what they deſign'd to do with me; I call'd however five or ſix times for my Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and I recover'd again from a languiſhment, which made me find more ſorrow in Life than in Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He who had taken care of me, came then and caſt himſelf on his knees near my Bed, and ask'd me a thouſand Pardons, in a manner worthy of pity and compaſſion; he proteſted to me, that if the Heavens had not given him ſtrength in ſaving me out of the Sea, to preſerve a Life which he thought he had taken from me, that he never had dar'd to appear before me; and that if Repentance deſerv'd that what was paſt ſhould be forgotten, there never had been one more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere than his, nor follow'd with greater remorſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:66334:86"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This confeſſion made me think there was ſome miſtake, and that I my ſelf was deceiv'd, in taking the Perſon who ſpoke to me for St.</hi> Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veur; <hi>I made him to expound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf again, and ſo ſoon as he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd me of the ſecret of his Action, I let him know that I was not in a Condition to owe any ill will to any body; that I hop'd in a ſhort time to be rid of theſe evils which overcame me, and that without any conſideration to thoſe Services which he had lately render'd me, I did freely forgive him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At that moment another faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs took me, which troubled him: Mean time the Storm ſtill continu'd, and we had got the fourth Day to the heighth of</hi> Tangier; <hi>the fifth the Wind chang'd, and permitted us to paſs the</hi> Streights, <hi>to go Land in</hi> Spain <hi>in the neareſt Harbour. Our Ship, which was bound for</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>finding it ſelf in the</hi> Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranian <hi>Sea, reſolv'd to go to</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noua
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:66334:87"/>
                  <hi>to take in ſome Goods on the account of the Merchants; but the Sea, which ſeem'd to oppoſe it ſelf to all our Deſigns, kept us ſhut up at</hi> Valencia <hi>during three whole Months: There I ſuffer'd all that could be imagin'd; and if that St.</hi> Sauveur <hi>had not continued his Cares towards me, I believe that I had not eſcap'd the Waves, but to die preſently after on Land. He found out a Maid to ſerve me, and gave Money to the Captain of the Veſſel to lend me, not daring to offer me any himſelf. It was then that he related to me all that his Enterprize had made him to ſuffer, and that thinking himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to live, he was reſolv'd to go to</hi> Carolina, <hi>there to paſs his Life like a true Hermit; that in that deſign he had took Shipping for</hi> England, <hi>but that the Packet-boat having ſtricken againſt their Veſſel in the Road, it had been broke to pieces, the Storm not permitting ſo much as to ſave the Crew: That I
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:66334:87"/>had happily faſten'd my ſelf to a Plank, which the Waves had caſt on their Deck, and ſo had preſerv'd me from an unavoidable danger; he added, that mov'd with Compaſſion, he himſelf had carried me into a Cabbin, near to two</hi> Dutch <hi>Women, whom he intreated to take care of me, and to put me into a Bed, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he came to know me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, when he was bringing ſome Cordials to comfort me; that he had long doubted of the reality of this Adventure, and that he never was fully convinc'd of the Truth till he had heard me ſpeak. At this Recital he ſhed Tears, which mov'd me, whatever I could ſay, that this laſt Action did ſufficiently repair all that a too violent Paſſion had formerly inſpir'd him with to my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage; his Melancholy increas'd, by which he contracted ſuch a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which kill'd him in few days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I confeſs to you, that I was affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted at it, and that he had at leaſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:66334:88"/>the ſatisfaction in dying, to perceive the ſorrow which his loſs caus'd in me: We being in a Country, whence he could draw no Conſolation but from himſelf, I thought it neceſſary for me to ſee him, and I dare ſay that he was overjoy'd in thoſe laſt Moments, to hear me pray to God for him; he had oblig'd me to look after his Money, with which he had preſented me in the time of neceſſity, which I accepted not, but on condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to return it to his neareſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. Thus did I ſee expire a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who had given me different oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of Love and Hatred to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him. I was ſo accuſtom'd after that Death to ſuffer whatever Fortune prepar'd for me of good or evil, that I look'd without the leaſt concern on the wrong which ſhe thought to have made me, in caſting us from the Coaſt of</hi> Italy, <hi>whence we were not far, into this Harbour, which appears to me ſafe, through the pleaſure which I receive
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:66334:88"/>to find you here, and to ſee you again with the ſame generous Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of which you had given me ſuch fair Proofs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Hubert,</hi> impatient in his turn, to give her an account of his ſufferings, and of thoſe troubles he had endur'd, related to her all his Travels, and omitted nothing of what could give her ſtrong Ideas of his paſſion; he then found that at <hi>Roan</hi> he had taken the Maid for the Miſtriſs, and that it had been an hard piece of buſineſs not to have been deceived; beſides thoſe Cloaths which he had met with at the <hi>Jewry</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and all the other Circumſtances, did but too much confirm him in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; ſo that he lookt as a Miracle on the return of a Perſon, who according to all appearance had been ſwallow'd up by the Sea, he would have given her new Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his Love, when the Governour came in, and expreſs'd
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:66334:89"/>the ſhare he had in their mutual joy.</p>
               <p>He bid them afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what meaſures to take, before he gave advice at Court of her ſeiſure; that it was of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to take them very exact, and then leaving his friend Maſter of his fair Priſoner, with the means to ſee one another, he diminiſh'd by that generous act all that could remain in them of ſorrow and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. According to all appearance there was but little remedy to be found to wholly free themſelves from troubles, and had ſhe not reſolv'd to diſpute of Religion with him, at that time he intended to ſpeak of nothing but of Love, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure that ſhe had never ſeen an end of her miſeries.</p>
               <p>She was perfectly inſtructed in the Roman, as well as in her own, and the Knight being accuſtomed to hear her frequently decide di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Controverted points, he began
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:66334:89"/>to receive that which proceeded from her delicate mouth as O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and at laſt was of Opinion, that in ſpight of his Director he might enter into a particular exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of his Belief. That hard uſage againſt the poor Proteſtants had already given him ſome Ideas of their Innocence, and of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of their Cauſe, he a-new conſulted his own Conſcience, and pierc'd by thoſe Inſtructions that were given him, he believ'd that without allowance to his Love, he ought to be of the Religion of that Perſon whom he ſo tenderly lov'd.</p>
               <p>Madmoiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> had never yet felt ſuch a pure joy, as that which this Converſation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded her; her heart was ſo pleas'd at it, that ſhe ſcarce could manage its motions, ſhe let him know that it was by that way only, that he had made an end of Conquering her, and that in time ſhe ſhould give him the ſtrongeſt and moſt
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:66334:90"/>ſolid aſſurances of it; mean time, ſecrecy was to Conduct a buſineſs of that importance, and this happy Change was to remain ſacred for all the reſt of the World. The Major was perſwaded that Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu</hi> had reſolv'd in Marrying of St. <hi>Hubert</hi> to wed his Religion alſo; by that means he had the pleaſure to give to his advice what colour he pleas'd; and an anſwer to it being come by the next Poſt but one, he gave them no longer time but to advertiſe Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle of <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> and Monſieur of St. <hi>Hubert</hi> of the reſt of their Adventures, and of their Marriage, which was perform'd very ſecretly. Their departure troubled him, being ſorry to part with ſo good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, he gave them ſome marks of his trouble by his Civilities, they alſo expreſs'd the Obligations they had to him; and that amiable Company took the way into their own Province; they were no
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:66334:90"/>ſooner got thither, but they thought of conveying a geat deal of means out of the Kingdom, and after what manner they ſhould retire. They choſe a truſty Gentleman to make a Voyage into <hi>Switzerland,</hi> to ſe whether that Road would be more ſafe than the others; he was at <hi>Geneva,</hi> where he ſojurned two days with a Friend, where having receiv'd full Intelligence on his Journey, he return'd to give an account of his Commiſſion: That paſſage appearing dangerous, St. <hi>Hubert</hi> had a fancy which he thought very ſeaſible. The Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons were ſtill in the <hi>Piedmont,</hi> where they were making an attempt to deſtroy the Inhabitants of the Vallies: Though his duty did no longer call him to it, he loſt no time, but got thither, to gain a paſſage out that way. He had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree'd with <hi>Chanlieu,</hi> who had Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his Siſter, that to ſecure more of their means, he ſhould remain
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:66334:91"/>ſome time longer in <hi>France;</hi> that he ſhould give out that St. <hi>Hubert</hi> was not ſo long abſent, but to ſeek after his Wife who had ſtoln away from him. That he ſhould change his Name, and by that means he ſhould give him ſecret advices of all his Affairs.</p>
               <p>This Reſolution being taken, he convey'd part of his Means into <hi>Holland,</hi> where he had friends, and being got to <hi>Turin,</hi> with a great Equipage, he went to the Camp, whence he return'd to ſee his Wife at the appointed meeting place; they paſs'd through the <hi>Milaneſe,</hi> and took the great Road into <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and from thence the Road to <hi>London,</hi> where one may remain as <hi>incognito</hi> as in <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:66334:91"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
